<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first fruites of the Gentiles In three sermons preached in the cathedrall church at Sarum. By Bartholomevv Parsons Batchelor in Divinitie, and vicar of Collingborne-Kingstone, in the county of Wiltes.</title>
            <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114080</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1030:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first fruites of the Gentiles In three sermons preached in the cathedrall church at Sarum. By Bartholomevv Parsons Batchelor in Divinitie, and vicar of Collingborne-Kingstone, in the county of Wiltes.</title>
                  <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes for I. H[arrison] and Edw. Blackmore, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Blazing Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Harrison's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The first fruits of the Gentiles.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14448:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14448:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST FRVITES OF THE <hi>GENTILES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In three Sermons Preached in the Cathedrall <hi>Church at Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By BARTHOLOMEVV PARSONS Batchelor in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, and Vicar of Collingborne-Kingſtone, in the County of Wiltes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESAY 60 3.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Gentiles ſhall come to thy light — thy ſonnes ſhall come from farre.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes</hi> for <hi>I. H.</hi> and <hi>Edw. Blackmore,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Blazing Starre, 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14448:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14448:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, GEORGE MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUES of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Viſcount <hi>VILLEIRS, Baron of</hi> Whadon, <hi>Iuſtice in eyre of all his</hi> Maieſties <hi>Forreſts, Parks,</hi> and <hi>Chaſes</hi> beyond Trent, <hi>Maſter of the Horſe to his</hi> Maieſty, <hi>and</hi> one of the Gentlemen of his Maieſties <hi>Bed-Chamber,</hi> Knight <hi>of the moſt Noble order of</hi> the <hi>Garter,</hi> and one of his Maieſties moſt Honorable <hi>Priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough my meaneſſe of conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, my baſhfulnes of diſpoſition be very ſtrong Remoraes to ſtay me from preſſing like <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, with a preſent, of ſuch poore Fruits as my barren ſoyle yeeldeth into the preſence of your Honor, whom not a <hi>Rex gentium</hi> only,<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 43.11.</note> a <hi>Pharaoh, Aſſuerus,</hi> or <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> but ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:14448:3"/>a King as for his Intellectuall, Morall, Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Theologicall Vertues, and Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Globe of this Earth hath not borne till this preſent, hath <hi>made a great man in his Kingdome, giuen many great gifts vnto</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 2.48.</note> and whoſe ſeate hee hath ſet aboue many other of his Nobles, becauſe hee findeth the ſpirit of God, euen an excellent ſpirit of <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion</hi> in you,<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 41.38.39.</note> which hath a Magneticall Virtue to draw <hi>the fauour of a King towards it</hi> by the teſtimonie of the wiſeſt King that GOD gaue to his old people of the Iewes:<note n="c" place="margin">Dan. 1.17.18 19. c Prou. 14.35.</note> Yet my ſecond (and I hope my better) thoughts yeelde mee motiues, to counteruaile theſe retractiues and incouragements: to preponderate theſe diſcouragements. For to preſume ſo farre, and ſoare ſo high in this Dedication, I am not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle emboldened by the generall, and conſtant Fame of your Honors Heroicall, and Benigne diſpoſition, who (according to that of <hi>Antiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes: That Virtue and true Nobilitie goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Laortius lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Labor to excell others, as well in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde: as greatneſſe of place; and to vſe that fauour and grace which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you with his royall Maieſtie, not with <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalon</hi> to popular inſinuations &amp; applauſes:<note n="e" place="margin">Sam. 15.16.</note> nor with <hi>Haman,</hi> to make your ſelfe terrible by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing decrees againſt opoſites,<note n="f" place="margin">Eſt. 3.8.</note> but with <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> to doe good amongſt your people, and ſeeke the welfare of them,<note n="g" place="margin">Neh 2.</note> with <hi>Ebedmelech,</hi> to deliuer thoſe that are in diſtreſſe,<note n="h" place="margin">Ier. 38.</note> and with
<pb facs="tcp:14448:3"/>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> to become a ſuitor, for the ſetting of men of <hi>Wiſedome and Vnderſtanding ouer the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Realme,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 2.49.</note> who not only ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo gracious and clement a King, but alſo taſting ſo deepely of the fountaine of his <hi>Fauors</hi> cannot but imimate ſo glorious; and reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a patterne: As they that walke in the Sunne muſt needes be coloured by the Sunne, and as that woman in the Goſpell, to whom much loue was ſhewed in the forgiueneſſe of hir many ſinnes, could not but ſhew much loue againe in pious Offices.<note n="a" place="margin">Luke 7.37.</note> As then <hi>Alexander</hi> the great determined about the relinquiſhing of his Kingdome, when hee was readie to die, that it ſhould bee <hi>Optimo et genereſtſsimo,</hi> fo I <hi>(ſi parua licet componcre magnis)</hi> about the dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating of theſe my vnpoliſhed Labours, that it ſhall be to him, <hi>that is ſo good and generous.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the dignity of the ſubiect miniſtreth fuell to the fire of my <hi>boldneſſe</hi> in this kinde. For if <hi>Dauid</hi> durſt ſpeake of Gods Teſtimonies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Princes<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 119.46.</note> happily thoſe Princes that did ſit and ſpeake againſt him, and perſecute him<note n="c" place="margin">Ibid. v. 23. &amp; 161.</note> for his loue to Gods Law; how much more may wee that are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, dare both to ſpeake and wright of any of the glad tidings of his Goſpell to a <hi>Theophilus, a friend of God,</hi> that is perſwaded of the certainty of them<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 1.4.</note> and to whom, they are the very Ioy and reioycing of his heart? And if <hi>Paule</hi> thought it no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption but happineſſe, to ſpeake in defence
<pb facs="tcp:14448:4"/>of his religion before king <hi>Agrippa,</hi> who could bee but almoſt perſwaded to bee a Chriſtian,<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 26.28.</note> how much more may euen a <hi>minimus Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolorum</hi> be bold in the Lord to declare <hi>(Voce aut Scripte,)</hi> any part of the Goſpell of Chriſt to a <hi>Sergius Paulus,</hi> a prudent deputy, who both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to heare the word of God, and beleeueth it.<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 13.7.12.</note> who is all out a Chriſtian, and beleeueth the Prophets, euen all the holy men of God that wrote by diuine inſpiration. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p>As then that <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> whoſe prayſe is in the Goſpell, ſpecially dedicateth both his bookes (which yet were publiſhed for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall benefit of all the houſhould of Faith) to that excellent <hi>Theophilus,</hi> who was (as the Greeke Scholies ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a Gouernour,</hi> (for ſo that ſtile of <hi>Excellent</hi> giuen to the Gouernours <hi>Felix</hi> and <hi>Feſtus</hi>) euineeth:<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 23.26. &amp; 26.25.</note> So I who haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted all my paines to the Goſpell of Chriſt, haue trodden in his ſteps, in tendring a part of them (which I now make publicke to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that are in Chriſt) to your Honour; who with <hi>Zabud</hi> are a <hi>principall Officer</hi> about our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. King 4.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And it cannot bee but that your Honour, ſtanding a ſeruant before the Throane of our <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. King 10.8.</note> who is aſwell an <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> as a <hi>Rex</hi> in our Ieruſalem<note n="e" place="margin">Eccle. 1.1.</note> and whoſe wiſedome excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not only the wiſedome of the children of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. King 4.30.</note> (the periſhable wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world) but euen the wiſedome of
<pb facs="tcp:14448:4"/>the ſonnes of the Prophets amongſt vs, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing of doubts, deciding of controuerſies, impugning of the common aduerſarie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of Prophecies, interpreting of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult places, and diſcourſing readilie vpon any Probleme propoſed concerning the great things of Gods Law, muſt be both in lightened with a great meaſure of vnderſtanding therein, and inflamed with a feruent zeale and affection thereto. For ſuch is the rauiſhing beautie of diuine learning, that the more it is ſeene, the more it is admired, the more you vnderſtand with <hi>Daniel</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 9.1.</note> the more you will ſet your heart to vnderſtand, and to queſtion about theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred miſteries,<note n="b" place="margin">Dan 10 &amp; 12.8.</note> which maketh mee hope that your Honor will vouchſafe to taſte of this <hi>Manna,</hi> though dreſſed after the contrarie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, to liſten to theſe Songs of <hi>Sion,</hi> though ſung out by my harſh voice, and played to on the Harpe by my vnskillfull hand, and to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne theſe Meditations though vttered by a ſlow tongued <hi>Moſes,</hi> not one whoſe tongue is as the penne of a ready writer, by a country <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> not a courtly <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and by him that is rude in ſpeech, not one that commeth with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of words.</p>
            <p>And ſo I tender them to your Honour in all humilitie, with that farewell benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his Sonnes going into <hi>Egypt, God Almighty giue you Fauour in the ſight of the Man.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 43.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14448:5"/>
Now the Lord of Lords, who hath brought your Honour hitherto, faſten you as a nayle in a ſure place, bleſſe your Houſe, that it <hi>may continue</hi> for euer before him, and after ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Dayes, Ritches and Honour, heere on Earth, giue you the fulneſſe of Ioyes in his preſence in Heauen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all humble Duty, <hi>BARTHOLOMEVV PARSONS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14448:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The firſt fruits of the Gentiles.</head>
            <head type="sub">In three Sermons preached in the Cathedrall Church at Sarum.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MAT. 2. VERS. 1.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Now when Ieſus was borne in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Herod</hi> the King, behold there came wiſe men from the <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Saying, where is he that is borne king of the <hi>Iewes?</hi> for wee haue ſeene his Starre in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and are come to worſhip him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot but ingeniouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg heere with <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> that <hi>Multa nobis opus eſt vigilantia, &amp;c. Wee haue neede of much watchfulneſſe, many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that wee may paſſe through and learne the difficultie of this preſent place,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 6. in Mat.</note> For the ſtrife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the heard-men of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> Cattell, and the heard-men of <hi>Lots</hi> Cattell, about their paſturage<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 13.7.</note> was neuer ſo great, ſo irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable as the ſtrife betweene the ſheepeheards of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14448:6"/>is heere, what theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Wiſemen were, what their Profeſſion, what their Countrie, when they came thence, at what time after <hi>Chriſts</hi> birth they came to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> what this ſtarre was, when and how it firſt appeared and roſe, how it guided them in their Iourney, one (as it was in the caſe of <hi>Ahab</hi>) <hi>Saying on this manner, and another on that manner</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. King. 22.20</note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes being againſt Ephraim, and Ephraim againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes, and both of them againſt Iudah,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 9.21.</note> Amongſt all which varieties, and extreamities, I holde it the beſt diſcretion to keepe that which is good for edification,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.20.</note> to caſt away that which is but the fewell of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, rather to finde out and follow that <hi>which may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the edifying which is in Faith:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>then to doate about vaine and vnprofitable queſtions</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>which doe but gender ſtrife</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.23.</note>. To come to the Text then, there is a word in it and it is <hi>Ecce, Behold,</hi> which is <hi>Nota attentionis promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens rem magnam, a note of attention, promiſing ſome great matter to follow after,</hi> which ſerueth as an Index to poynt out vnto vs many admirable remarkeable things here related, and which ſtandeth as a Beacon on an hill, to diſcouer a ſtrange and vnexpected com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and enquirie, not of enemies, but of friends, for the new borne <hi>Mesſias,</hi> accompanied, and attended, with many circumſtances of Times, Places, Perſons, Cauſes, and Ends, all of them full of admiration. For is it not wonderfull in our eyes that ſuch perſons <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Wisemen</hi> ſhoulde come and enquire for him, <hi>that they which ſate in darkeneſſe ſhould ſee great light</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Matt. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>and that light ſhould ſpring vp to them, which ſate in the region, and ſhadow of death, that they to whome he was not ſpoken of ſhould ſee, and they that haue not heard, ſhould</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 52.12.</note> 
               <hi>vnderſtand</hi> any thing of him,<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>who comming amongſt his owne, was not receiued by his owne,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 15.21.</note> 
               <hi>could haue none honour in his owne Countrey,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 13.57.</note> 
               <hi>Nato Chriſti exultabat Chaldea</hi> (ſaith <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>)<note n="m" place="margin">Maxim. 9. homill in hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>When Chriſt was borne Chaldea was glad, and all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14448:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hieruſalem with her princes was troubled, the Iewe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted him, the wiſe man adored him, Herod whetted his Sword, the wiſe man prepared his gifts,</hi> that they ſhould come at ſuch time as this king was newlie borne, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no forme nor comelineſſe, no beautie, that hee ſhould be deſired,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſai 53.2.</note> no better Chayre of ſtate then an Oxes Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note n="b" place="margin">Luke 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>before he had knowledge to refuſe the euil, &amp; to chooſe the good,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſai. 7.15.</note> and in the dayes of <hi>Herod the</hi> King, who to attaine and maintaine his Crowne, ſpared neyther Prieſt nor presbyterie, rooted out all the poſteritie of <hi>Dauid</hi> that hee could finde, butchered the Infants of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> made hauock of all the nobilitie of <hi>Iury,</hi> yea, hated his owne fleſh, killed his owne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pheroras,</hi> his owne wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> with all her kinred, his owne Sonnes, <hi>Ariſtobulus, Alexander</hi> and <hi>Antepater,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ioſeph An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. lib. 16. c. 17.</note> that they ſhould come from the Eaſt, leauing their owne people, and their fathers houſe, and beeing followers of the obedience that was in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braham,</hi> the Father of this new borne King, <hi>who went out of his Countrie, and from his kindred, and fathers houſe, vnto a Land that God ſhewed him,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note> with the religious <hi>Eunuch: goe ſo farre a Iourney to worſhippe,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 8.27.</note> that they ſhould come to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that ſo <hi>Iſraell might know, that God might prouoake them to Iealouſie by them that are no people; and anger them by a fooliſh Nation,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 10.19.</note> and <hi>Vt ſtudio magorum damneretur, pigritia Iudaeorum</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Remigius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Thomam in catena.</note> 
               <hi>by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of the wiſe-men: the ſluggiſhneſſe of the Iewes might be condemned,</hi> that they ſhould come by the guidance of a Starre, God creating a new Starre, not to giue light by night,<note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 31.35.</note> but to bee a light to lighten theſe Gentiles, that they might ſee, and finde the way to that ſtarre of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Num. 24.17.</note> of which <hi>Balam</hi> had fore-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied, and calling them: <hi>per ea quae familiaria ijs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo faciebat,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil 6. in Matt.</note> 
               <hi>by thoſe things which cuſtome made fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar vnto them,</hi> that they ſhould come to worſhippe him, looking not on the things which were ſeene, his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14448:7"/>outward contemptible appearance, his beeing in the forme of a ſeruant: but on the things which were not ſeene, his eternall God-head and power, his being in the forme of God, and his thinking it no robberie to be equall with God,<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> yea and acknowledging him which was <hi>Rex Iudaeorum, King of the Iewes,</hi> to bee alſo <hi>Rex Seculorum:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt ſerm. 31. de temp.</note> 
               <hi>the eternall King, magnum aliquod la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebat in paruo</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>)<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt ſerm. 35. de temp.</note> 
               <hi>there lay hidde ſome great thing in that little one, which thoſe men the firſt fruits of the Gentiles, which came ſo ſuppliant from ſo farre, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by heauen that ſhewed it, not by the earth that brought them and by adoring they deſired to obtaine the fauour of that: which by beholding they did not ſee.</hi> are not all theſe wonderfull wonders? are they not the great miſteries of Godlineſſe?<note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim: 2 16.</note> are they not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>The great workes of God,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 2.11.</note> worthy to bee publiſhed to the World with an <hi>Ecce,</hi> a note of attention: of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. The body, the ſumme of all heere is an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall narration, a deſcription of a ſolemne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: and enquirie for the new borne <hi>Mesſiah,</hi> which being as the Center hath many circumſtances, as the circumference compaſſing it about on euerie ſide, Firſt of the <hi>time when Ieſus was borne,</hi> which birth is farther illuſtrated either by the place, at <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Iudea,</hi> or the time <hi>In the dayes of Herod</hi> the king. Secondly, of the perſons who; <hi>Wiſe men:</hi> Thirdly, of the places eyther from whence? <hi>From the Eaſt,</hi> or whither? <hi>to Hieruſalem,</hi> Fourthly, of the forme of the inquirie: <hi>Where is he that is borne King of the Iewes?</hi> Fiftly of the moouing cauſe, <hi>Wee haue ſeene his Starre,</hi> Sixtly, of the finall cauſe and end, <hi>We are come to worſhip him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proſecute theſe in the order I haue propoſed them, I muſt beginne firſt with the time when all this was done, <hi>for to euery thing there is a ſeaſon, and a time to euery purpoſe vnder the heauen,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.1.</note> and that is <hi>Now when Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was borne,</hi> preſently vpon his birth all this falleth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14448:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>out: for hee that as long as hee was in the World, <hi>was the light of the World,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 9.5.</note> could not bee hidde after his comming into the world, <hi>Quis enim celauerit ignem, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine qui ſemper proditur ipſe ſuo</hi> (ſaith the Poet) <hi>for who can hide fire, which is alwayes diſcloſed by it's owne light, Latere inter obſcura ſaeculi, lumen caeleſti non poterat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Maximus</hi>)<note n="b" place="margin">Maximus ſerm. 2. in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</note> 
               <hi>the heauenly light could not be hid amongſt the darkeneſſe of the world,</hi> he that at his lifting vp vpon the Croſſe, would draw all men both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 12.32.</note> at his manifeſtation in the fleſh, doth preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to manifeſt himſelfe to the ſheepe-heards of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and to the wiſemen of the <hi>Gentiles, Noluit intra,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo,</hi>) <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Leo ſerm. 1. in Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>He would not haue the beginning of his birth hidde within the narrow corners of his mothers Houſe, but would preſently bee acknowledged by all men: who vouchſafed to be borne for all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here the wiſedome; or rather the curioſitie of man (which cannot content it ſelfe, with the reuealed things <hi>which are onely ours.</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> 
               <hi>but muſt make it ſelfe ouer-wiſe</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>eate of the forbidden Fruit: and prie into the Arke of God</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. Sam. 6.19.</note> cannot forbeare to enquire into the things that God hath ſecreted, nor keepe it ſelfe from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon the rocks of vaine, and vnprofitable queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, touching the very particular time, and day of their comming after our Sauiours Birth. And as in them that were guided by their owne coniectures: and not by any heauenly reuelation; there were ſundrie erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious oppinions about the Sauiour of the World, <hi>ſome ſaying, that he was Iohn Baptiſt, ſome Elias, others Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, or one of the Prophets,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Matt. 16.14.</note> ſo in this point wherein the Scriptures are ſilent: and haue reuealed nothing vnto vs, men following their owne coniectures, are deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their opinions: ſome ſaying, that they came the very day of <hi>Chriſts</hi> byrth, and worſhipped him with the ſheepeheards;<note n="i" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. 30. de temp.</note> ſome a little before the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins purification, ſome preſently after, ſome a yeere
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14448:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>after this byrth, ſome almoſt two yeeres after. All which if I ſhould at large diſcourſe of, or diſcuſſe, I might happilie builde vpon the foundation, Hay and Stubble, <hi>Vanas &amp; inutiles argutias,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Beza in 1. Cor. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>vaine and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quirkes:</hi> which would bee but matter for the fire, enough for the preſent, that our Churche hath thought fit for a memoriall of theſe mens comming vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to celebrate the twelfth day after his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie: and to note withall vnto the diſputers heerea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, that if the wiſedome of the ſpirit, (which hath ſingled out thoſe things to be written, <hi>quae ſaluti cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentium ſufficere videbantur,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. tract 49. in Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>which ſeemed ſufficient for the ſaluation of them that beleeue,</hi>) had held the preciſe knowledg of the particular time ſo neceſſary, it would as well haue recorded it: as the very time of the <hi>Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards</hi> comming to ſee him, which was the very day of his birth,<note n="c" place="margin">Luke 2.11.15.</note> Howbeit the very Phraſe vſed by the HOLY-GHOST <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ieſus being borne or as ſoone as Ieſus was borne:</hi> importing that they came with as great celeritie and ſpeede, as ſo large a Iourney could be accompliſhed, it ſhall bee good and profitable for vs<note n="d" place="margin">Tit. 3.8.9.</note> (auoyding fooliſh queſtions) to learne by this which is written for our inſtruction, to doe that which we heere and ſee in them heere; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>make haſt, and delay not to keepe Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>to make no tarrying to turne vnto the Lord, nor to put it of from day to day,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 119.60.</note> 
               <hi>but to ſeeke the Lord whilſt hee may bee found, to call vpon him whileſt hee is neere,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Eccle. 5.7.</note> that is requiſite in all the duties of godlineſſe, which is required in our vowes, <hi>that wee muſt not bee ſlack to pay them,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſai 55 6.</note> &amp; as whereſoeuer the Goſpell ſhould bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the whole world: that worke of the Woman, which powred an Alablaſter boxe of precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 23.21.</note> vpon the head of our Sauiour: was to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in memoriall of her,<note n="k" place="margin">Matt. 26.13.</note> ſo whereſoeuer the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Gods ſeruants is recorded; the haſte that they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14448:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>vſed the diligence that they gaue, is euer remembred, as that which crowneth the worke, <hi>Abraham</hi> beeing enioyned to circumciſe himſelfe and his familie, doth it <hi>the ſame day,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17.23.</note> to ſacrifice his ſonne, riſeth vp <hi>Earlie in the morning to goe about it,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 22.3.</note> 
               <hi>Cornelius</hi> to ſend for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who muſt ſpeake <hi>vnto him words, whereby hee ſhould be ſaued, doth it immediatly,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 10.33.</note> 
               <hi>Paule,</hi> to goe vnto the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to open their eyes, and turne them from darkeneſſe to light, doth it <hi>immediatly: without commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating with fleſh and blood,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Neſcit tarda molimina, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti gratia,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on <hi>Luke,</hi>) <hi>the grace of the holy Ghoſt, cannot skill of any ſlow enterpriſes.</hi> How ſharpely then are the men of this generation to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked, who ſay of the building of the ſpirituall Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in their hearts: as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Temple, <hi>the time is not yet come,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Hag. 1.2.</note> who with the <hi>Iewes, will not in this their day: know the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto their peace,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luke 19.41.</note> but are content that their legions of ſinnes which poſſeſſe them; as ſo many deuills (for <hi>Quot crimina, tot Doemonia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, how many ſinnes, ſo many deuills,</hi>) ſhould ſay vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> when hee commeth to caſt them out: as the Deuills that hee came to diſpoſſeſſe, <hi>art thou come hither to torment vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time?</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Matt. 8.29.</note> and who when they ſhould heare Gods <hi>voice to Day,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 95.7.8.</note> putit of till to Morrow, as<note n="i" place="margin">Exo. 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did praying for him,<note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. in. confeſſion.</note> 
               <hi>Quamdiu cras, cras, quare non modò, quare non haec horâ finis turpitudinis meae,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>How long? to morrow, to morrow, why not now, why in this very houre is there not an end of my filthines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this firſt circumſtance of <hi>Chriſts</hi> birth: is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified eyther by the place or the time, the place: <hi>In Bethlehem of Iudea,</hi> it maketh no matter whether wee reade here <hi>Bethlehem of Iudea, or of Iudah, Iudea,</hi> beeing put, not for the whole Countrie of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but for the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> as elſe-where; <hi>Ioſeph hearing that Archelau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> raigned in Iudea would not goe thither, but tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14448:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>aſide into the parts of Galilie.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 2.22.</note> Now this addition ſerueth here for a diſtinction betweene it and another, <hi>Bethlehem</hi> in the Tribe of <hi>Zabulon,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iud. 19.15.</note> 
               <hi>duae Bethlehem ſunt</hi> (ſaith the ordinary gloſſe) <hi>there are two Bethlehems,</hi> one which is in the <hi>Land of Zabulon,</hi> another which is in the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Iudah, which was firſt called Ephrata.</hi> And for this <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> the place of <hi>Chriſts</hi> birth, Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> hath well obſerued that<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt de concord. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangel.</note> 
               <hi>Matthew and Luke doe agree concerning the Citty of Bethlehem: but how and for what cauſe Ioſeph and Mary came thither, Luke declareth; Matthew omitteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When our Sauiour then was conceiued in the wombe of his mother at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and by all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſhould in her purpoſe haue beene borne there, both <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> are compelled by the decree of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> to goe to <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> the Citty of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> to be taxed there becauſe they were of the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luke 2.4.5.6.</note> God ſo making a way for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Prophecie: which fore-told the place of his birth. Oh come hither then, and behold the works of the Lord; yea the mightie hand of our God, who, as in the great worke of the Creation, hee made the light out of darkeneſſe, ſo in the wonderfull workes of his prouidence, and preſeruation: can out of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill actions of men and deuills, bring forth good: and turne thoſe things which they doe for the ſatiſfying of their ſinfull wills; to the executing of his holy, and righteous will. <hi>Deus ſuas voluntates vtique bonas, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet per malorum voluntates vtique non bonas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt in Enchirid cap. 101.</note> 
               <hi>God can fulfill his wills beeing good, by the wills of wicked men that are not good.</hi> Thus when Ioſephs brethren thought euill againſt him in ſelling him for a ſlaue into <hi>Egypt:</hi> God meant, and turned it to good, to ſaue much people aliue thereby.<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 50.20.</note> As then the expert Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian can ſo temper, and compoſe the poyſon of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents: that it ſhall bee a preſeruatiue againſt poyſon:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14448:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo the great Phiſition of our Soules, did ſo maſter, and ouerrule the poyſonfull action of the traytor <hi>Iudas,</hi> who betrayed his Maſter, and through couetouſneſſe, made merchandiſe of him that his ſhipes became a plaſter to heale vs,<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 53 5.</note> and the ſelling of him, made him ours, as <hi>Rabanus</hi> ſaith ſweetely, <hi>Exulta Chriſtianae.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rabanus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Ludol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum de u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta Chri. part 2. part. 52.</note> 
               <hi>And reioyce O Chriſtian, for by the merchandize of thine enemies thou haſt gotten the victory, that which Iudas ſolde, and the Iewe bought, thou haſt gotten, for Chriſt is ours not the Iewes, which bought him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the things which befell our Sauiour in the dayes of his fleſh, came not to paſſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luke 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>By chaunce,</hi> but were done either for the fulfilling of ſome promiſe or propheſy, or for the expreſſing of ſome miſtery, let vs a little examine why <hi>Bethlehem</hi> is the place of his byrth. Not to heape vp al that might be ſaid heerein, it was in reſpect; firſt either of former prediction, ſecondly, preſent condition, thirdly, or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſignification; firſt, of former prediction: hee that came in the fullneſſe of time, would be borne at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem;</hi> for the fullfilling of former both prophecies and promiſes: for ſo it was fore-prophecied, <hi>that out of Bethlehem Iudah: ſhould he come forth that was to be ruler in Iſraell.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Micah 5.2.</note> And heere by the way, the very place of his byrth doth ſerue like a <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> to point out, to demonſtrate him to be the Lambe of God, the verie God, the very Chriſt:<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 4 29.</note> ſo that as the things which <hi>Iohns</hi> deſciples that he ſent vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaw and heard the works that he did, did teſtifie of him; ſo the place where hee was borne, ſheweth that this is hee that ſhould come, and none other is to bee looked for.<note n="g" place="margin">Matt. 11.3.4.5.6.</note> And ſo it was fore-promiſed to <hi>Dauid,</hi> yea; bound with the indiſſoluble bond of an Oath, (that God would not ſhrinke from) <hi>that of the fruite of his wombe, hee would ſet vpon his Throane</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 132.11.</note> yea, <hi>ſuch a ſeede which ſhould endure for euer, and whoſe Throne ſhould bee as the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14448:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sunne before God,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal 89 36.</note> which muſt neceſſarily bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of that bleſſed ſeede of the Woman, which ſhould <hi>bruiſe the Serpents head,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> of that branch that ſhould grow out of the roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 11.1.2.</note> at whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception the Angell promiſed to the Virgin: <hi>that God ſhould giue vnto him the Throane of his father Dauid, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 1.32.33.</note> And then where ſhould this ſeede promiſed to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> be more fitly borne: then in that Towne which was eſpecially denominated of him? the Citty of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and where hee himſelfe was borne; where ſhould the roote of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> firſt ſprout out: but in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> the towne of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> the <hi>Bethlehemite?</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Sam. 16.1.</note> Now that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre all things to edification and inſtruction, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but cry out with our bleſſed Sauiour:<note n="f" place="margin">Matt. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>Happy are our eyes that ſee</hi> or may ſee: heere is this particular, the truth of that generall laid downe by the Apoſtle, <hi>That all the promiſes of God made in Chriſt are in him, yea, and in him Amen:</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.20.</note> hath he ſaid, and ſhall hee not doe it? hath he ſpoken, and ſhall hee not make it good?<note n="h" place="margin">Num. 23.19.</note> It is one of his properties wherby he proclaimed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and would bee knowne to the whole World to be <hi>aboundant in truth,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Exo. 34.6.</note> that is <hi>ſuch an one as keepeth couenant and mercy with his ſeruants.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Kin. 8.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Oh then beloued, let vs that are the heires of grace, ſeeing the immutability of Gods counſell; haue ſtrong conſolation<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 6.17.8.</note> againſt all either outward ſtriuings, or inward terrors, that would ſeeme to ſeparate vs from the loue of God in <hi>Chriſt: and ſeeing hee is faithfull, that hath promiſed: let vs holde faſt the profeſſion of our faith without</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>wauering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, our Sauiour was borne at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the preſent condition of the place, a poore place was fitteſt for his birth: that made himſelfe poore for vs.<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>A Citty little amongſt the thouſands, of Iudah,</hi> (a thing which the ſpirit of God taketh notice of,<note n="o" place="margin">Micah 5.2.</note>) meeteſt for him to be borne in, <hi>who made himſelfe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14448:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of no reputation, and tooke upon him the forme of a ſeruant,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ſerui ſuſceperat formam</hi> (ſaith Leo<note n="b" place="margin">Leo ſerm. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi in Epiphan.</note>) <hi>&amp;c he that tooke on him the forme of a ſeruant, and cam not to iudge, but to be iudged, choſe Bethlehem aforehand for his natiuity, &amp; Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem for his paſſion.</hi> A City ſo meane, that it is not reko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in the number of thoſe Cities that fell by lotte vnto the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioſh 15.</note> for him that ſhould haue <hi>neyther forme nor beautie,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſai. 53 2.</note> but muſt bee <hi>the ſhame and contempt of the people</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 22.6.</note> If the wiſedome of the fleſh ſhould haue beene Gods counſellor, to haue taught him<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 40.13.</note> it would rather haue aduiſed to make choiſe of <hi>Hieruſalem, the Citty of God</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 87.2.</note> the <hi>Ioye of the whole Earth,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lam. 2.15.</note> where the wiſe men ſought him, or of <hi>Rome,</hi> that was then the head of the World, (<hi>Romanos rerum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos</hi> ſaith the Poet about this time, <hi>the Romanes that were Lords of all,</hi>) then of <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> ſo ignoble a place: But the Lord, to ſhew that his waies are not as mans wayes, his thoughts, as mans thoughts,<note n="i" place="margin">Iſai. 55.8.</note> that his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is made perfect in weakeneſſe<note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor 12.9.</note> and that hee hath choſen the weake things of this World, to confound the things which are mighty,<note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.27.</note> honoured this meane village, with the byrth of the Sauiour of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simaximam Romanam, eligiſſet Ciuitatem, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tho. Aquinas,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Thom. <hi>3.</hi> part queſt. <hi>35.</hi> artic. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>If he had choſen that great city Rome men would haue thought that the change of the World: had come through the power of the Cittizens: If hee had beene the Sonne of the Emperour, they would haue attributed the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that came by him to his power: But that it might bee knowne that the God-head had altred the World, hee choſe a poore Mother, and a poorer Countrie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To giue heere ſome briefe touch of inſtruction as I paſſe along; the meaneneſſe of our Sauiours birth, in ſo contemptible a Towne, yea; in a ſtable, the baſeſt place in the Inne, his lodging in a Cratch, for a Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſerueth to pull the Peacocks feathers of the high-minded ones of this world, who glory ſo much in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14448:11"/>fleſh; of the <hi>Nebuchadnezars,</hi> who ſtand ſo much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their great Babels that they haue built for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their Maieſtie,<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 4.29.</note> of the vaine-glorious boaſters, that bragge ſo much of their earthly Burges ſhippes,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 22 28.</note> that reioyce becauſe their wealth is great, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their hand hath gotten much;<note n="c" place="margin">Iob. 31.25.</note> that glory in their ſtrength, in their wiſedom, in their ritches, or in any outward things, which (as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid of meates:) commend vs not vnto God.<note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.8.</note> That we may the better caſt away this ſinne of vaine-glory, which cleaueth ſo faſt vnto vs: we are to looke vpon the patterne which <hi>Ieſus</hi> the author and finiſher of our faith, hath left vs herein, we muſt for lowlines of minde, haue the ſame minde in vs which was in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of no reputation.<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Quae ſuperbia ſanari potest</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi>) <hi>what pride can be healed, if it be not healed by the humbleneſſe of the Sonne of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Bethlehem</hi> is the place, in regard of a future and miſticall ſignification, I will rather vtter it in the words of the ancients then mine owne. <hi>Locus iſte Bethlehem</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Chriſoſt. hom 1. ex uariis in Matt.</note>) <hi>This place of Bethlehem, where the Lord was borne, had a prophetical name: for Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem out of the Hebrew, is interpreted the houſe of Bread, becauſe here the ſonne of God muſt be borne, who is the bread of life, according to that which he himſelfe ſaith in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, I am the bread of life, which came downe from heauen.</hi> Almoſt the ſame words ſpeaketh <hi>Gregorie</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Gregor. hom 8. in Euangel.</note> that out of the mouth of two witneſſes the matter might bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed. <hi>Bene etiam in Bethlehem, &amp;c. well alſo is hee borne in Bethlehem, for Bethlehem is interpreted the houſe of Bread, for it is he that ſaith I am the Bread of life, which came downe from Heauen: therefore the place wherein the Lord is borne, is beforehand called the houſe of bread, becauſe it ſhould come to paſſe that he ſhould there bee borne in the ſubſtance of fleſh, who ſhould with inward fulneſſe refreſh the mindes of the Elect.</hi> The interpretation howſoeuer it be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14448:11"/>Allegoricall, neede not be offenſiue, becauſe it is Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall, agreeing to the proportion of faith,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12 6.</note> At ſuch times then amongſt vs, wherein, as wee haue heard, ſo we muſt ſee in the citty, &amp; church of our God<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 48 8.</note> wherein we muſt not only heare with eares: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſee with our eyes, and handle with our hands, the word of life,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.1.</note> and bread of life, it ſhall not bee an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable meditation for vs to conſider: that he who gaue his body for vs vpon the Croſſe, and now giueth it to vs in the Sacrament, would bee borne at <hi>Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem,</hi> that thereby hee might ſhew himſelfe to bee the true bread of life, that cometh downe from Heauen, and giueth life to the World,<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 6 33.35.</note> that eating thereof, we might liue and not die,<note n="e" place="margin">Ibid. verſ. 50.51.</note> and alſo that as <hi>Euſebius E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſenus</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="f" place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſſ. hom. in hoc E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangel.</note> we muſt bee <hi>Bethlehems,</hi> houſes of bread, ſpirituall Temples, in whome Chriſt muſt bee formed,<note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> and in whoſe hearts he muſt dwell by faith,<note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Simus nos Bethlehem,</hi> (ſaith he) &amp;c. <hi>Let vs be Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem, let vs be the houſe of Bread for he which will not bee the houſe of Bread muſt periſh, for this the Lord himſelfe ſaith, vnleſſe yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man: yee ſhall not haue life in you, let vs therefore receiue Chriſt in our houſe, let vs receiue him in our mind and heart, Let him be borne in vs.</hi> Now after the deſcription of the place, followeth the mention of the time of our Sauiours Byrth: <hi>In the dayes of Herod the King</hi>] in the dayes, an hebraiſme, <hi>quo optime exprimitur,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Beza in Luc. 1.5.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Whereby it is well expreſſed, how ſhort and fading is the power euen of good Kings, much leſſe that the tirrany of ſome ſhould be perpetuall. Of Herod</hi>] ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the great <hi>King</hi>] of <hi>Iudea,</hi> as hee is called <hi>Luke</hi> 1.5. And hee is ſo called to diſtinguiſh him from <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod Antipas</hi> the Tetrarch of <hi>Galile,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luke. 3.1.</note> and <hi>Herod Agrippa</hi> his nephew, that butchered S. <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 12.2.</note> of which three the common verſe runneth
<q>
                  <l>Aſcalonita necat pueros Antipa Iohannem,</l>
                  <l>Agrippa, Iacobum mittit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in carcere Petrum.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14448:12"/>
The infants, kills great Herod. Antipas the Baptiſt ſlayes,</l>
                  <l>And I ames, Agrippa kills, and Peter in the Priſon layes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now this accurate mention of the time, is not for the times ſake onely: but there is a further miſterie in it, <hi>Hoc non tantum ponit,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hierome</hi>)<note n="a" place="margin">Hier. in locum</note> 
               <hi>The holy writer bringeth this in: not only in regard of the time; but that that might appeare to bee fulfilled, a prince ſhall not depart from Iudah,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> 
               <hi>till Shiloh come, ponit tempus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>6.</hi> in Matt.</note>) <hi>&amp;c. hee mentioneth the time that he might bring to our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory the olde prophecie of the Patriarch Iacob, who hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diligently mentioned the time vnto vs, and gaue an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſigne of the coming of Chriſt ſaying, a prince ſhall not depart from Iudah, &amp;c. Huius ineffabilis miſerecordia ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtatio,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>)<note n="d" place="margin">Leo homil. <hi>3</hi> in Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>the manifeſtation of this vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercy, came to paſſe at ſuch time, as Herod was King of the Iewes, euen when the lawfull ſucceſſion of Kings ceaſed, the power of the high prieſts was deſtroyed, and a ſtranger bare rule, that the true kings byrth might bee prooued by that prophecy which had ſaid, a prince ſhall not depart from Iudah.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 46.10.</note> 
               <hi>Or as wee reade the Scepter ſhall not depart from Iudah.</hi> As then <hi>Bethlehem</hi> was the place, ſo the days of <hi>Herod,</hi> are the time of his natiuitie, that ſo, that might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, which God almoſt two thouſand yeares before, had ſhewed by the mouth, and laſt words of that bleſſed Patriarch <hi>Iacob,</hi> for now the ſcepter was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Iudah,</hi> the royall power that from that time had beene inueſted in that Tribe, was now pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from it, and none of the ſeede of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſate vpon the Throane of the kingdome, but <hi>Herod patre Idumes, et matre ortus Arabica,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rupertus</note> 
               <hi>Whoſe Father was an Edomite and his mother an Arabian,</hi> being created King by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and the ſenate of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ioſeph <hi>Antiq lib.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> into whoſe hands at this time, God had giuen the whole World,<note n="h" place="margin">Luke 2.1.</note> now alſo was a Law-giuer departed from betweene his feete, for whereas till this time the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14448:12"/>Elderſhippe of the ſeauentie Iudges (which were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the houſe of <hi>Dauid</hi>) ſtood and had iudiciall power, this <hi>Herod in the thirtieth yeere of his tyrannicall rule,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Philo Iudeus de partibus imp.</note> 
               <hi>deſtroyed the Sanhedrim of the houſe of Dauid, and foyſted in a Sanhedrim of proſelytes-becauſe it was ſaid that Chriſt promiſed in the Law, was now borne,</hi> ſo that now: hee that was to come, muſt come, the fulneſſe of time was now come for God to ſend <hi>Shiloh,</hi> euen him that was made of a Woman:<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4 4.</note> borne of a Virgin that had not knowne a man.<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 1.34.</note> As then the finding of him wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſwadling clouts, and lying in a Manger, is a ſigne to the ſheepe-heards, that hee is the new borne <hi>Meſſias,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 2.12</note> ſo the finding of him in the fleſh, at ſuch time as God, (who onely can declare the end from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and from ancient times, the things that are not yet done,<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa 46.10.</note>) had fore ſhewed by the mouth of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that he muſt come: is a ſigne vnto vs that hee is the horne of ſaluation, raiſed in the houſe of <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 1.69.</note> as being none abortiue, borne out of time, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in due ſeaſon, euen in the fullneſſe of time, that was appointed for him.</p>
            <p>Now then in that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is rayſed vp heere in the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to be the glory of Gods people <hi>Iſraell,</hi> at ſuch time as in outward ſhewe his glory ſeemed to ceaſe, and his Throane to be caſt to the Ground,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 89.44.</note> in that when the heathen were come into Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 79.1.</note> and they that hated them ruled ouer them<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 106.41.</note> God did ſo graciouſly looke downe from Heauen, and viſit them, and his hand was vpon the man of his right hand<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 80.17.</note> 
               <hi>ideſt ſuper Chriſto filio delectionis eius, that is, vpon Chriſt his beloued ſonne,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iunius in pſal. <hi>80.</hi>
               </note> and vpon the Sonne of man, whom he had made ſtrong for himſelfe, to lift him vp to be a Prince, and Sauiour vnto <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 5.35.</note> this is as a word behind vs<note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 30.21.</note> to tell vs, that God is euer nereſt to his Church; when he ſeemeth to be fartheſt of, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14448:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>then he looketh with the tendreſt eye of his mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the affliction of his people, when in all outward appearance he ſeemeth to haue forgotten to be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and to haue ſhut vp his louing kindneſſe in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 77.7.</note> yea to caſt off for euer: and vtterly to breake promiſe with his people, and that when all ordinarie humane meanes fayle, then God ſendeth helpe from on high. <hi>When the Lord ſeeth that there is no man, his arme bringeth forth Saluation,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 59.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>when my Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſake me</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 27.10.</note>) ordinary meanes, vſuall helpes fayle, <hi>then the Lord taketh me vp. Bono a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo eſtote ſocij</hi> (ſaith <hi>Philo Iudeus,</hi> when hee ſaw the Emperour <hi>Caius</hi> angry with his frends) <hi>bee of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage fellows: becauſe Gods helpe muſt needs bee at hande, when mans helpe fayleth. When the poore and needy ſeeke water: and there is none, and their tongue fayleth for thirſt, I the Lord will heare them, I the God of Iſraell will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 41.17.</note> When <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> were olde, and ſtricken in yeares, and there was no more poſſibilitie of iſſue to come from them: then of fruite from a dead ſtock; then is the ſeede ſo often promiſed giuen vnto them, and <hi>Sarah</hi> beareth a childe in her olde age.<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 21.2.</note> when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was fold into <hi>Egypt</hi> for a bondſlaue, when his feete were hurt with fetters, and hee laid in Iron,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 105.18.</note> when his Soule did cleaue vnto the duſt, and his belly vnto the ground, hee being come to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Ebbe, and to be euen, <hi>Infra infimos, Lower then the loweſt,</hi> then; euen then: the Lord rayſed him out of the dungeon: to ſet him with the princes of Egypt, and made him ruler ouer the land,<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 41.43.</note> when the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans made the Iſraelites to ſerue them with rigor, and made their liues bitter with hard bondage, when they commanded all the male children (that were <hi>ſpes gregis the hope of poſterity</hi>) to be deſtroyed, ſo that there was little hope, either of continuing poſteritie, or of retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> (which God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14448:13"/>to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſterity,<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 13.15.</note> then the eyes of the Lord out of his holy habitation looke vpon their affliction, and then is his right hand ſtretched out, to deliuer them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to bring them into that good land that hee promiſed,<note n="b" place="margin">Exo. 3.1.</note> when <hi>Egypt</hi> purſued them after their departure,<note n="c" place="margin">Exo. 14.9.</note> and there was behinde them an army of <hi>Egyptians:</hi> before them the Red-Sea, ſo that their hearts fayled them: then the Lord wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wonders in the Sea, and leadeth them through the depthes; as through the<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 106.9.</note> wilderneſſe. When to <hi>Gideon,</hi> (iudging according to the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: and by the miſery which they indured vnder the <hi>Midianites</hi>) the Lord ſeemed to haue departed from <hi>Iſraell:</hi> then was he with them,<note n="e" place="margin">Iud 6.13.</note> then did hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to helpe them. When <hi>Daniell</hi> muſt into the Lyons Denne, and the King himſelfe, though hee laboured till the going downe of the Sonne, could not deliuer him out of the hands of his Enemies; then is his God whom he ſerueth: able and willing alſo to deliuer him from the Lyons: and to ſhutte their mouthes that they ſhall not hurt<note n="f" place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> him. And when <hi>Ionah,</hi> though the <hi>Mariners</hi> tow hard to bring him vnto the Land, muſt needes into the Sea, ſo that hee thought himſelfe caſt out of Gods ſight:<note n="g" place="margin">Ion. 2.4.</note> then doth God prepare a great fiſh to ſwallow and ſaue him,<note n="h" place="margin">Ion. 1.17.</note> cauſing Saluation, to come out of the deſtroyer, as meate out of the Eater.<note n="i" place="margin">Iud. 14.14.</note> It is then a faithfull ſaying vttered in the ſong of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 32.36.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord will repent himſelfe for his people, when hee ſeeth that their power is gone, and that there is none ſhut vp or left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this aſſurance, that God will ſtand with vs, when all the world forſaketh and fayleth vs: muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vs in all our trouble, the end whereof wee cannot ſee, the meanes to wade out of which we cannot find, it muſt bee armour of proofe to keepe off all feares, which through the weakeneſſe of our faith are readie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14448:14"/>to enter into our hearts<note n="a" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 8 26.</note> 
               <hi>Etſi fractus illabatur orbis, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the world ſhould breake in peeces and fallon vs: God is our refuge and ſtrength</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> 
               <hi>a very preſent helpe in trouble therefore will we not feare though the Earth bee remooued, and though the Mountaines be carried into the midſt of the Sea, though the waters thereof roare and bee troubled, and though the Mountaines ſhake with the ſwellings thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue but begunne to ſpeake of the matters, and miſteries in this text, and the ſwiftneſſe of the time, the ſharpeneſſe of the weather inioyne mee to ſilence, and to hold my peace from farther good words. I will then according to our Sauiours counſell,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.12.</note> gather vp the fragments that remaine, concerning theſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, their Countrie, their comming to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> their enquirie for the new borne King, the moouing cauſe and end of their comming, and when I haue a conuenient time, propoſe them vnto you.</p>
            <p>To God the Father that ſent his ſonne made of a Woman, and made vnder the Law for vs, to the ſonne that tooke on him the forme of a ſeruant, and made himſelfe of no reputation for vs; and to the holy ſpirit, which muſt leade vs into the trueth of theſe high and heauenly miſteries, three perſons and one God, bee honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14448:14"/>
            <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Ionah</hi> at his ſecond ſending brought the ſame meſſage to the Niniuites, ſo I comming againe amongſt you bring the ſame matter and text, and as I promiſed gather vp the fragments, the ſundry circumſtances of this Text that were left vnhandled. In the ranke of theſe circumſtances next to the time of their comming <hi>Chriſts birth</hi> (of which with the amplifications coincident thereunto, I haue ſpoken many things) followeth the circumſtance of the perſons that come and make this enquiry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold wiſe men came.</hi> Now heere againe are vaine reaſonings amongſt the interpreters, ſtrifes to no profit, but to the troubling and amaſing; of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.14.</note> what theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>wiſe men were,</hi> what their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was, whether they were Philoſophers, Prieſts, Aſtrologers, Sorcerers, Kings or States-men, <hi>Non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum inter eos tantam componere litem,</hi> I meane not to arbitrate the firſt betweene them, for <hi>cui bono?</hi> what good is there in it? whether they were all, any or many of theſe, it mattereth not, <hi>dummodo ſalua maneat hiſtoriae veritas, as long as the truth of the Hiſtory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſafe</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Beza in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note>. Onely to ſpeake that for which wee may haue ſome light out of the text it ſelfe, it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be moſt probable that they were Aſtrologers, <hi>Viri ſiderum inſpectionibus aſſueti</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Cyprian. Sermon. de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; ſtella.</note> 
               <hi>Men acuſtomed to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14448:15"/>gaze vpon the ſtarres, &amp; ſpectandorum ſiderum arte pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Leo Serm. <hi>4.</hi> de Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch as were skilfull in the art of gazing vpon the ſtarres,</hi> ſuch as amongſt the Chaldeans, were called by the Prophet, Viewers of heauen and Starre-gazers,<note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 47.13.</note> becauſe they are lead heere by a ſtarre, to ſeeke out this ſtarre of <hi>Iacob</hi> that was newly ariſen.</p>
            <p>Amongſt our aduerſaries the Papiſts (who ſpeake things that they ought not for filthy lucres ſake<note n="c" place="margin">Tit. 1 11.</note>, it is an vnwritten tradition, and therefore (ſay they) to be receiued <hi>Pari pietatis affectu, With the like deuotion that the Booke of the Old and New are</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſeſſione. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>, that they were Kings, three Kings becauſe they brought three gifts, that their bodies after their death were tranſlated from their Country to Conſtantinople, from thence to Millaine, from Millaine to Colon, whither at this day there is great reſort of the ſimple people (who like the Athenians are in all things too ſuperſtitious<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 17.22.</note>, to adore them as holy reliques. And, to fill vp the meaſure of their fayning, they haue found out three names for them alſo, <hi>Iaſpar, Melchior,</hi> and <hi>Balthazar.</hi> And to this purpoſe they bring or rather wring and wreſt the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>the Kings of Tarſhiſh and of the Iſles ſhall bring preſents: the Kings of Sheba and Seba ſhall offer gifts</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.10.</note>, But, <hi>conſtat hoc ex picturâ non ex ſcriptura</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">D. Boys poſtill in Epiphan.</note>, it is a tale painted on a wall, not written in the word. And their owne men are againſt them herein, <hi>Nec veterum interpretum quiſquam hos Magos reges vocat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ianſenius</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ianſenius concord, cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>not one of the old interpreters calleth theſe wiſe men Kings.</hi> And <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Mantuan: in Faſtis Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec reges vt opinor erant, neque enim tacuiſſent</l>
               <l>Hiſtoriae ſacrae authores genus iſtud honoris.</l>
               <l>As I thinke ſure they were not Kings,</l>
               <l>for then the men that wrote;</l>
               <l>The Holy Hiſtorie, would this,</l>
               <l>ſo great an honour note.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14448:15"/>
               <hi>Maldonate</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Maldo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. in loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, and <hi>Baronius</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ton. <hi>1.</hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>, make no more of them but regulos, petty Kings, ſuch as thoſe fiue that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſubdued<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 14.</note>. And for the text of the Pſalme, they muſt turne about the earth (the foundation whereof God hath ſo laide, that it ſhould not be remooued for euer<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 104.5.</note>) they muſt <hi>ex Meridie &amp; Occidente facere Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> (as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith they haue done<note n="e" place="margin">Calu. in Matt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>turne South and Weſt into Eaſt,</hi> before it will crowne them Kings, <hi>Saba &amp; Arabia reſpectu Ieruſalem planè in Meridie, non in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riente</hi> (ſaith their owne <hi>Ianſenius</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſen. vbi ſupra.</note>) <hi>Saba and Arabia in reſpect of Ieruſalem, are altogether in the South not in the Eaſt.</hi> But to leaue this vaine iangling <hi>de lana caprina,</hi> and to come to that whereby the Church may receiue edifying<note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.5.</note>, as our Sauiour firſt riſing from the dead, became the firſt fruits of them that ſlept in the earth<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.20.</note>, ſo theſe men that were Gentiles in the fleſh (and therefore aliens from the common-wealth of Iſraell, ſtrangers from the couenant, farre off both in place and grace) by comming firſt vnto Chriſt are here made the firſt fruits of the gentiles, wherby as by a patterne God would ſhew forth, that he would giue vnto the Gentiles repentance vnto life<note n="i" place="margin">Act 11.18.</note> 
               <hi>In iſtis fides gentium vt primitiae deo conſecratur</hi> (ſaith the ordinary gloſſe here) <hi>in theſe men the faith of the Gentiles is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated as the firſt fruits vnto God. Stellae ortus &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hillary</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Hil. in expoſ. huius Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>, <hi>the riſing of the ſtarre being firſt vnderſtood of the Gentiles, ſheweth that the Gentiles ſhould preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt. Ideo Magi &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>1.</hi> ex varij in Matt.</note>, <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wiſemen of the Gentiles were firſt choſen to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that by them the gate of ſaluation might bee ſet open to all the Gentiles.</hi> And he cryeth out elſe-where, <hi>O beati Magi &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Chryſ. in opere imperf. hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Oh happy wiſe men, who of all the Gentiles were vouchſafed to bee the firſt fruits of the faithfull, for thoſe wiſe men were a repreſentation of the Church that ſhould be afterwards. Illi Magi &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>32.</hi> de temp.</note>, <hi>Thoſe wiſe men, what were they but the firſt friuts of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14448:16"/>Gentiles? the ſheepheards were Iſraelites, the Wiſemen Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, they from nere, theſe from farre of, and both of them runne vnto the corner ſtone; for hee comming (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith) preached peace to vs which were farre off, and peace to them which were neere, for he is our peace, which hath made both one.</hi> And againe he ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt ſerm. <hi>30</hi> de tempore.</note>, <hi>Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt &amp;c. Hee was manifeſted in the very cradles of his infancy to them which were nere, and them which were farre off, to the Iewes by the neereneſſe of the ſheepheards, to the Gentiles by the farneſſe of the Wiſemen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then Chriſt aſſoone as euer he was borne, was (as old <hi>Simeon</hi> vttered in the ſpirit of prophecy of him) <hi>a light to lighten the Gentiles</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 2.32.</note>, for although God for a time to ſhew his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>manifold wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 3 10.</note>, ſet vp a partition wall<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note> of rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, whereby he hedged in the Iewes to be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious people and a chiefe treaſure to him aboue all the nations of the earth<note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 7.6.</note>, and excluded the reſt of the Nations of the world from his couenant, although hee gaue them his ſtatutes and his ordinances which hee did not to any Nations beſides<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 147.20.</note>, although to them <hi>pertained the adoption and the glory, and the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and the giuing of the Law, and the ſeruice of God, and the promiſes</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 9.4.</note> yet many and excellent things were euer vttered of the calling and comming in of the Gentles, of bringing them into the ſheepe-fold of the Church by Chriſt, who <hi>is the great ſheepe-heard of the ſheepe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 13.20.</note>.</p>
            <p>It was promiſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> that was the father of vs all<note n="i" place="margin">Rom 4 16.</note>, that in his ſeed (which is Chriſt<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 3.16.</note>, not the Iewes onely, but all the Nations of the earth ſhould bee bleſſed<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 18.18. and 22.18. Gal. 3.8.</note> It was fore-prophecied by <hi>Iacob,</hi> that <hi>Shiloh</hi> ſhould be <hi>expectatio gentium,</hi> or, <hi>to him ſhould the gathering of the people bee</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> by <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai,</hi> that hee ſhould <hi>bee the deſire of all Nations</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note>, by the Pſalmiſt, that <hi>all Nations ſhould ſerue this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14448:16"/>Solomon,</hi> this King of peace, and builder of the new Temple made without hands,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 72.11.</note> and that <hi>he ſhould haue the Heathen for his inheritance, and the ends of the Earth, for his poſſeſſion,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 2 8.</note> 
               <hi>by Iſai, that to the roote of Ieſſe ſhould the Gentiles come,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 11.10.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhould bring forth iudgement to the Gentiles,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 42.2.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhould not only bee Gods ſeruant to rayſe vp Iacob and Iſraell: but that alſo hee would giue him for a light vnto the Gentiles, that hee might bee his Saluation, to the ends of the World.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 49.6.</note> 
               <hi>And that the Gentiles ſhould come, to the light of Lion,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 60.3.</note> by <hi>Ieremias,</hi> that <hi>the Gentiles ſhould come vnto the Lord, from the ends of the earth, and ſay: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Fathers haue inherited Lies, Vanitie, and things wherein is no profit.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 16.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that we may not drinke vp the whole Sea, to ſhew that the water is Salte,<note n="h" place="margin">Ireneus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. haereſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> bring all out of the treaſurie of the prophets, that is ſtored vp in this kind, let me tell you in one word, that of that horne of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation rayſed vp in the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> not onely to be the glory of Gods people <hi>Iſraell:</hi> but alſo to bee a light, to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his holy Prophets, which were ſince the world began.<note n="i" place="margin">Luke 1.70.</note> And that which God hath ſo ſpoken, he maketh haſt (as it were) to fulfill by bringing theſe firſt fruits of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as ſoone as euer the bleſſed ſeede: (in whom all nations muſt be bleſſed) was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the fleſh: to receiue the promiſed bleſſing from him. <hi>In his impletum eſt illud,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Maximus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Maximus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil <hi>2.</hi> in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</note>) <hi>In theſe wiſe-men is fullfilled, that which was foretold by the Prophet: they to whome he was not ſpoken of: ſhall ſee, and they that haue not heard, ſhall vnderſtand.</hi> Yea, and that we may ſee greater things then theſe,<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 1.50.</note> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that were Gods only people: are now none of his people: that were the naturall branches, are broken of, and we grafted in; that were Gods owne houſhould: haue their houſe left deſolate, and wee are come to bee of the houſhould of faith, and fellow Cittizens with the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14448:17"/>Saints,<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.19.</note> that were the children of the Kingdome; are caſt out into vtter darkeneſſe, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> come from the Eaſt and Weſt, and ſitte downe with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> in the Kingdome of Heauen.<note n="b" place="margin">Matt. 8.11.12</note> Thus hath God taken away his vineyeard, from thoſe husbandmen, that refuſed to yeelde him fruite; euen the Kingdome of God from them, and giuen it to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 21.41.</note> Let mee heere then ſpeake the words of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to vs <hi>Gentiles;</hi> hath God done ſo great things for vs; and ſhall not our ſoule magnifie him, &amp; our ſpirit reioyce in him? Hath he called vs out of darkenes; into his marueilous light? Hath he made vs a people, which were no people? Haue we obteyned mercy, that had not obtained mercy? And ſhall we not ſhew forth the prayſes of him that hath done this?<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9.10.</note> now wee ſee all this fullfilled in our eyes, ſhall it not make our hearts reioyce, &amp; our bones flouriſh like an hearb?<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 66.14.</note> could <hi>Dauid</hi> being taken from the ſheepecoate to bee ruler ouer <hi>Iſraell,</hi> wonder at the Lords doeing herein? <hi>who am I, O Lord God, and what is my houſe, that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Sam. 7.18.</note> And ſhall not we being taken out of the power of darkenes, and tranſlated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of Gods deere Sonne, euen a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that cannot be ſhaken,<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> an inheritance immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, vndefiled that withereth not,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> giue thankes vnto God the Father, that hath made vs meete to bee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the inheritance of the Saints in light?<note n="i" place="margin">Col. 1.12.14.</note> Could <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> ſo magnifie <hi>Dauids</hi> kindneſſe, for reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him the Lands that were <hi>Sauls:</hi> and making him eate bread at his Table? <hi>All my Fathers houſe were but dead men before my Lord the King, yet diddeſt thou ſet thy Seruant, among them that did eate at thine owne</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Sam. 19.28</note> 
               <hi>Table.</hi> And ſhall not wee that were dead in ſinnes, and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, ſing prayſes vnto our God, who of his good pleaſure doth giue vs a kingdom, that we had no right at all to: could lay no claime to, and maketh vs to eate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14448:17"/>bread, in the kingdome of Heauen. <hi>His igitur dilectiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi, diuinae gratiae, myſterijs eruditi</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Leo. ſerm. <hi>3.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>) <hi>therefore beloued, let vs which are inſtructed in theſe miſteries of Gods grace, celebrate the day of our firſt Fruits, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the calling of the Gentiles with all poſſible Ioy, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thankes to our mercifull God, who hath made vs meete,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>to be partakers of the inheritance, of the Saints in light, who hath taken vs out of the kingdome of darkeneſſe: and tranſlated vs into the kingdome of his deere Sonne. Becauſe as Eſaias prophecied, the people of the Gentiles, which ſate in darkeneſſe ſaw great light, and light, is riſen to them: which dwelt in the region of the ſhadow of Death. Of whome the ſame Prophet ſaith vnto the Lord, the Gentiles which knew thee not: ſhall call vpon thee; and the people which were ignorant of thee: ſhall ſhe vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might heere againe gather, that which the Holy-ghoſt hath ſcattered, that Chriſt in bringing theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers, Sorcerers, practiſers of curious Arts,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 19.19.</note> that had runne away fartheſt from him, to be the firſt fruits of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> vnto him, and in calling theſe <hi>Diaboli vates ad ſui adorationem prae caeteris, theſe prophets of the Diuell to worſhippe him before others,</hi> yea in ſtirring vp <hi>Gentium primitias ex ipſis inferorum penetralibus</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Beza ex Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unc lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> 
               <hi>the firſt Fruits of the Gentiles, out of the very priuie chambers of Hell,</hi> would (in vouchſafing mercy to theſe chiefe of ſinners) ſhew forth all long ſuffering, for a pattern to them which ſhould hereafter beleeue on him to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Idcirco magis eluxit,</hi> &amp; (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Chryſoſt. homil. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x variis in Mat.</note>) <hi>therfore the grace of God ſhined vnto the wiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Gods goodnes might be manifeſtly known, &amp; no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might deſpaire that ſaluation might bee giuen him vpon his beleeuing: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee now ſaw it giuen to the wiſe-men.</hi> But though we may finde much honny here, it is not good to eate too much honny,<note n="f" place="margin">Prou. 25.16.27.</note> nor good to cloy you with too much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one matter. I paſſe therefore from the perſons to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14448:18"/>the next circumſtance of the places and firſt of the place from whence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Eaſt.]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>from the riſing of the ſunne the ſenſe is from the Eaſt Countrey, or which in reſpect of Iudea, is ſcituated towards the Eaſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Piſcator in locum.</note>, Now in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the Eaſt, <hi>I am praeſignabatur &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. ſermon. <hi>31</hi> de tempore.</note>. <hi>was now foreſignified that which afterward the Lord ſayd, many ſhall come from the Eaſt &amp;c. Quoniam ab oriente vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Chryſoſt. upere imperf. in Matt. hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>,) <hi>Becauſe they came from the Eaſt whence the day ſpringeth, from thence did the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of faith come, becauſe faith is the light of our ſoules. Bene ab oriente &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Maximus</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Maximus homil. <hi>4.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>) <hi>they are well ſaid to come from the Eaſt, who come to worſhip that euerlaſting day-ſpring, of whom it is ſayd, and the day ſpring from an high hath viſited vs. Merito ſanè ab Oriente veniunt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Bern ſerm <hi>3.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>) <hi>they come worthily from the Eaſt, which publiſh vnto vs the new riſing of the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe, which enlighten the whole World with ioyfull newes.</hi> But theſe are happily <hi>magis florida, quam ſolida,</hi> haue in them more flouriſh of witte then ſoundneſſe of Diuinity, therefore I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them as <hi>Iehu</hi> to the meſſenger of <hi>Iehoram, turne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde me</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. King. 9.18.</note>.</p>
            <p>Now as before about their profeſſion, ſo here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine about their Countrey, there is a doore of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie ſet wide open, &amp; there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 28.29.</note>, <hi>much reaſoning,</hi> amongſt the fathers and interpreters about this Eaſt Country from whence they came, whither it were Perſia, or Chaldea, Arabia, or Ethiopia, Egypt or Meſopotamia. And it is but a poore conciliation, that a F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ier giueth, who to reconcile all theſe diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities ſaith <hi>Dicamus ex varijs locis veniſſe, vnum hine, alium illinc, tertium aliunde</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kierus con ione <hi>10.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>, <hi>let vs ſay that they came from diuerſe places, the one from hence, the other from thence, the third from ſome place elſe;</hi> much like to the confutation that hee maketh of our anſwere, that the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14448:18"/>wiſemen which came from the Eaſt, could not bee the Kings of Tarſhiſhe, of Sheba and Seba<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 72.10.11.</note>, becauſe thoſe Countries are South from Ieruſalem, in which reſpect the Queene of Sheba that came to heare <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> wiſdome is called the Queene of the South<note n="b" place="margin">Luk 11.13.</note>, <hi>Nos non dicimus</hi> (ſaith he<note n="c" place="margin">Boskierus con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ione <hi>6</hi> in Epiphan.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>We doe not ſay that they came out of Tharſis, Sheba, and Seba, but that the Kings of Tharſis, the Kings of Saba, the Kings of Arabia came, for they might bee Kings thereof, and yet not come from thence, but from another part of their Kingdome, as I may ſay that the King of Spaine came, though hee come not out of Spaine, but out of India or Seicily,</hi> I may ſay of him as <hi>Auſtin</hi> of his aduerſary, <hi>vbi reſpondere cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, magis oſtendit quod non poterit reſpondere</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. literas Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliani lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>when he indeuoureth to anſwere, then he ſheweth moſt of all that he cannot anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the point in queſtion, although there bee faire probability that this Eaſt Country is Perſia, both by the ſcituation of it which lieth Eaſt from Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea<note n="e" place="margin">Cyrill. in Iſa. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> orat: <hi>4</hi> vide Ptolomei tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las.</note>, and alſo by the name <hi>Magi,</hi> here giuen them (which as <hi>Peters</hi> language bewrayed him to be a Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilean<note n="f" place="margin">Matt. 26.73.</note>,) ſheweth them to be Perſians, being <hi>nomen meré Perſicum, a meere Perſian name, nomen profeſſionis, a name of profeſſion</hi> (as ſaith the Commentator vpon <hi>Prudentius</hi>) <hi>Quod genus ſapientum &amp; doctorum habeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Perſis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tully</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Cicero lib. <hi>1.</hi> de diuinatione.</note>) <hi>which kinde of wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men was to be found amongſt the Perſians,</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue profeſſed from the beginning to a voyde fooliſh and vnprofitable queſtions, from which wee can reape no edification, either in faith or in loue, I will paſſe from it, and ſee what inſtruction, we that muſt follow the faith and conuerſation of them that haue gone before vs in the faith<note n="h" place="margin">Hebr. 13.7.</note>, may gleane from hence. Their action then in comming ſo farre out of the Eaſt, from their fathers houſe and kinred, which it is hard to fleſh and bloud to leaue (for that is a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14448:19"/>point that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter muſt bee Catechized in<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal 45.10.</note>) from their natiue ſoyle, which <hi>neſcio quâ dulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine cunctos afficit</hi> (as the Poet ſaith) <hi>is vnſpeakeably ſweere vnto all men,</hi> to ſeeke and ſee Chriſt the new borne King of the Iewes in a ſtrange land, muſt bee our inſtruction to ſeeke Chriſt as well where, as while he may be found, to goe farre for him, to leaue all things with the holy Apoſtles, and follow him<note n="b" place="margin">Matt 19.27.</note>, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to forſake houſes, brethren, ſiſters, father mother, wife, children, or lands for his ſake<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 29.</note>. <hi>For, patrem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hieron. ad Furiam de viduis ſeruand.</note> 
               <hi>Honour thy father, if hee doe not ſeperate thee from the true father: otherwiſe</hi> licet patvulus &amp;c<note n="e" place="margin">Hieron. ad Helio. lorum de vita Eremit.</note>. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thy little Nephew ſhould hange vpon thy necke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thy mother with her haire about her eares, and her garments rent, ſhould ſhew thee the breaſts, wherewith ſhee nurced thee, although thy father ſhould lie on the Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, tread vpon thy father to goe ouer, paſſe away with drie cres to the banner of the Croſſe. It is a chiefe point of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſhew thy ſelfe cruell in ſuch a matter.</hi> And if the Queene of the South, came from the vttermoſt parts of the earth to heare the wiſdome of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 12.42.</note>, about hard queſtions and riddles<note n="g" place="margin">1. King. 10.1.</note>, if there came of all people from all the Kings of the earth, to heare the wiſdome of <hi>Solomon,</hi> vttering prouerbs, and ſpeaking of the nature of trees, beaſts, foules, creeping things and fiſhes<note n="h" place="margin">1. King. 4.33.34.</note>, (all which is but the periſhable wiſdome of this world<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 2 6.</note>,) how much more ought they, that deſire to bee filled with the knowledge of GOD, in all Spirituall Wiſdome and vnderſtanding<note n="k" place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note>, (as the Spouſe of Chriſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about the City in the Streetes, and in the broad waies, to ſeeke him whom her ſoule loueth<note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 3.2 4.</note>, and giueth not ouer till ſhee finde him) goe from ſea to ſea, from North to Eaſt<note n="m" place="margin">Amos. 8.11.12.</note>, (af God ſend ſuch a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fammin in any Land) to ſeeke him that is greater then <hi>Salomon,</hi> in whom are hidden all the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14448:19"/>treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note>, and who is made vnto vs that wiſdome<note n="b" place="margin">Cor. 1.30.</note>, whereby we become wiſe vnto ſaluation? if the Eunuch, being a man of great authority vnder <hi>Candace</hi> Queene of Ethiopia, and hauing charge of all her treaſure, forgot and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke both honour and Country, eaſe and dignity (being ſo many remora's to fleſh and bloud, which will pitty it ſelfe, that theſe things may not be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it<note n="c" place="margin">Matt. 16.22.</note>) to come ſo farre for Gods great name<note n="d" place="margin">2. Chr. 6.32.</note>, to come to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to worſhip God in a kinde of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that ſtood in carnall rites and ordinances<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 9.10.</note>, which were but the rudiments of the world<note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 4.3.</note>, but ſhadowes of things to come<note n="g" place="margin">Col. 2.17.</note>, how much more ought wee with that great multitude<note n="h" place="margin">Mar. 8.1.3.</note>, to come from farre, to ſhake off all worldly, either pleaſures or profits which cumber vs, that wee may with <hi>Philip</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 1.45.</note>, finde the Meſſiah, the Chriſt, who is the body and ſubſtance<note n="k" place="margin">Col. 2.17.</note>, who is the mediator of the <hi>New teſtament</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note>, yea who is ſurety of a better teſtament<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 7.21.</note>, and in whoſe face God doth giue vs the light of the knowledge of his glory<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note>, Nay, if wiſemen, the diſputers of this world, <hi>Plato</hi> being <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter Athenis,</hi> a Maiſter at Athens<note n="o" place="margin">Hieron. Epiſt. ad Paulin. Presbyt.</note>, <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> whoſe words were as Oracles to his Schollers, trauailed ouer many Countries, <hi>vt fierent diſcipuli, &amp; aliena diſcerent, that they might become ſchollers, and learne other mens doctrines,</hi> if <hi>Apollonius</hi> the Philoſopher went almoſt through the whole world, <hi>vt inueniret vbique quód diſceret</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Hieron. ibid.</note>, <hi>that hee might finde euery where ſomewhat to learne,</hi> to get the wiſdome of this world, which GOD will deſtroy<note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.19.</note>, and bring to nothing; ought not wee that are children in vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that naturally cannot perceiue the things of GOD<note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note>, that know nothing as we ought to know<note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.2.</note>, to compaſſe ſea and land (if the candleſticke of the Goſpell ſhould not ſtand in our habitations) that wee might follow Chriſt Ieſus, ſit at his feere<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 10.39.</note>,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14448:20"/>heare his preaching, and learne the wiſedome of God in a miſtery, euen the hidden wiſedome, which God, ordayned before the world to our glory,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, when the Famine was in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> went downe into <hi>Egypt</hi> once &amp; againe, to buy foode for the famine of their houſes,<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 42. &amp; 43.</note> and ſhall not the true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> be as wiſe for their Soules: as they for their bodies? Labour more for the meate which endureth to euerlaſting life: which the Sonne of God ſhall giue vnto them, then they for the meate that periſheth?<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> And with <hi>Cornelius</hi> fetch <hi>Peter</hi> from <hi>Ioppae,</hi> to ſpeake vnto them words: whereby they may be ſaued<note n="d" place="margin">Act 10.5.</note> when he is not to be had at <hi>Ceſarea: Pharaohs</hi> daughter bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be married to <hi>Solomon,</hi> (which marriage was a Type of the miſticall vnion, betweene Chriſt, and his Church) muſt forgett hir owne people: and hir Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, that ſhe might be brought in to the King, and hee take pleaſure in her beautie,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 45 10.</note> and they that will bee the ſpouſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> married vnto him, in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe and in mercy:<note n="f" place="margin">Hoſ 2.19.</note> muſt ſhake off all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections to Countrie or Kinred, to the World and the things of the World, (which hange on like ſo many clogges to keepe them backe, lie in the way like ſo many Lyons to hinder them) that they may runne after him, and bee brought into his chambers,<note n="g" place="margin">Cant. 1.7.</note> muſt hate Father, and Mother, &amp;c, <hi>That they may come to Chriſt, and bee his Diſciples.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 14.26.</note> And to bring the beſt Wine at the laſt, to take for an example him that was the friend of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iam. 2.23.</note> and Father of the faithfull.<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> when he was well ſtriken in yeares, being ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty fiue yeares old: ſo that hee could take no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in trauelling, getteth him out of his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and from his kinred and fathers houſe, where they ſerued other Gods:<note n="l" place="margin">Ioſ. 24.2.</note> leauing all, that he might goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Land which God would ſhew him to builde an Alter there vnto the Lord, and call vpon his name,<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 12.1.2.7.</note>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14448:20"/>and if we be <hi>Abrahams</hi> children, and of the houſhould of faith, wee will doe the workes of <hi>Abraham</hi> herein,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 8.39.</note> otherwiſe as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhewed his faith by this worke of his, in going out from <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and ſeparating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from amongſt them, and comming into the Land of promiſe, where hee ſerued the Lord, (for that, that was a fruit of his faith, the holy-ghoſt witneſſeth, b <hi>by Faith Abraham, when he was called to goe out into a place, which he ſhould after receiue for an inheritance, obeyed,</hi>) So on the other ſide, mens little faith, or rather flatte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie is ſhowne and knowne, as well as if it were written in their fore-heads with a penne of Iron, when with the rebellious <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in <hi>Moſes</hi> time: for the loue of the fleſh pots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they would rather tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Num. 11.5.</note> where they cannot Sacrifice to the Lord, without the abhomination of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Exo. 8.26.</note> then goe out into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> where they might freely Sacrifice vnto him, when with the Idolatrous Iewes, in <hi>Ieremies</hi> time,<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 44.17.18.</note> they can burne incenſe in <hi>Egypt,</hi> to the Queene of Heauen, and poure out drinke offerings to her, to enioy plenty of victuals: and keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues out of want; when with <hi>Lot:</hi> they can pitch their Tents neere <hi>Sodome,</hi> for the pleaſantneſſe of the Countrie;<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 13.10.12.</note> when with <hi>Martha,</hi> they trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about ſo many worldly matters, that they can neuer bee at leaſure to heare <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> and with thoſe in the parable, they preferre Farmes, Oxen, Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, Pleaſures, Profits, all before their ſpirituall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Matt. 22.</note> yea with the <hi>Gergeſens,</hi> will rather thruſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of their coaſts, then looſe their hoggs to enioy him:<note n="h" place="margin">Matt. 8.34.</note> and to come neere vnto our ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, where ſhall faith bee ſound amongſt the men of this generation, who when <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not now <hi>per lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginqua querendus, to be ſought farre off:</hi> when his word is not in Heauen? that we ſhould ſay, who ſhall goe vp into Heauen for vs, and bring it vs: nor beyond the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14448:21"/>Sea, that we ſhould ſay: who ſhall goe ouer the Sea for vs, and bring it vs, but is very neere vs,<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 30.12.13.</note> and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth plentiouſly amongſt vs, yea, when hee himſelfe dwelleth amongſt vs, hath his tabernacle in our coſts, from on high hath viſited vs, and walketh in the midſt of our Candleſtick,<note n="b" place="margin">Reu. 1.13.</note> when his Kingdome is come neere vs: will not goe out to meete him, will not with <hi>Nathaniell,</hi> come and ſee him,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 1.46.</note> with <hi>Zacheus</hi> ſtirre a foote, take a little paines to ſee him,<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 19.4.</note> nor with <hi>Dauid</hi> deſire to come into his Temple, to behold his beautie,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> to heare with their eares, to ſee with their eyes, and to handle with their hands, him being the word of life,<note n="f" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.1.</note> who when he riſeth vp earlie, and ſendeth vnto them his prophets, wiſemen and Scribes: will not receiue his prophets, in the name of a Prophet, but account the preaching of his word fooliſhneſſe,<note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.23.</note> and are ready with the <hi>Athenians</hi> to ſay of them that bring it: what will this babler ſay?<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 17.18.</note> Surely theſe men would be farre enough from going farre with theſe wiſe men to ſeeke him: if they will not receiue him when hee commeth amongſt them, if now, when he ſtandeth at their doore and knocketh: they will not let him in; with <hi>Zacheus</hi> receiue him to houſe. If when hee hath his houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: they will not come into his Courts, nor worſhip him in the aſſembly of his ſaints. amongſt the old people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> all the males muſt three times in the yeare, appeare before the Lord in the place which he ſhould chooſe to put his name in, euen in the feaſt of vnleauened Bread, in the feaſt of weekes, and in the feaſt of Tabernacles. Some of them then muſt come from farre, the Land being in length, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba,</hi> one hundred and ſixtie miles, &amp; in breadth, from <hi>Ioppa</hi> to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> fortie and ſixe miles.<note n="i" place="margin">Deut 16.16.</note> And to what a number all the males appearing,<note place="margin">Hieron. Epiſt. ad Dardanum.</note> (none being exempted vpon any worldly pretence) would amount, it may be gathered by that great multitude, that were
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14448:21"/>come to Ieruſalem, to keepe the Paſſeouer, when <hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian</hi> the Emperour beganne his ſiege againſt it<note n="a" place="margin">Ioſephus &amp; alij.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as the Hiſtories of thoſe times report <hi>tricies cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tena millia, thirty hundred thouſand.</hi> And whereas by the letter of the Law, the Males onely were bound to appeare, it is worth the marking, that the bleſſed Virgin would not take liberty in that kinde, but went with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to celebrate thoſe feaſts, <hi>the father and the mother of Ieſus went to Ieruſalem, after the cuſtome of the feaſt day</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 2.42.</note>.</p>
            <p>But in our daies, amongſt vs, when Gods worſhip is tied to no one place, neither to Ieruſalem, nor to the mountaine<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 4 21.</note>, but our Temples and Houſes of prayer, wherein Chriſt is to be found, are according to the number of our Cities and Townes, ſo that it is but a ſteppe to them that dwell neereſt, a Sabbath daies iourney to them that are remoteſt, to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, there are too many, that whereas they ſhould thrice a weeke appeare before the Lord, ſcarce tread in the Courts of the Lords houſe thrice in a yeare, that with <hi>Simeon</hi> they may ſee the Lord Chriſt<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 2.26.27.</note>, there are too many dainty dames amongſt vs, that are ſo farre from offering this free will offering with the Virgin, that they will not doe the leaſt part of that duty that is required of them in appearing before God in Sion, that are ſo farre from neuer departing out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with <hi>Anna</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 2 37.</note>, that on the other ſide, they almoſt neuer come into it, and had need to be dealt withal, as thoſe in the highwaies and hedges were, to bring them to the marriage feaſt<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 14.23.</note>, euen compelled by the vigor of authority to come in, that Gods houſe might be full on his Holiday. But enough hath beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the place from whence they come, I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proceed to ſpeake of the place whither they come. <hi>To Ieruſalem.</hi>] Ieſus being borne at Bethelehem, they come to ſeeke him at Ieruſalem. As the Church her
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14448:22"/>ſelfe at the firſt ſought her beloued, and found him not<note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 3.1.2. and 5.6.</note>, ſo theſe firſt fruits of the Church that God would call of the Gentiles, at the firſt ſeeking for Chriſt, finde him not. But how commeth it to paſſe (will ſome man ſay) that hauing runne well hitherto, they ſhould now goe out of the way, that hauing hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto followed the <hi>guiding of the heauenly light, and the ſhewing of the ſtarre that went before them</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Leo in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</note>, they ſhould now haue a miſt before their eies, &amp; wander in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? The anſwere is, that out of the context telling vs, that when they went towards Bethlehem, after their conference with <hi>Herode, behold the ſtarre which they had ſeene in the Eaſt, went before them againe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note>, <hi>Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere promptum eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Piſcator</hi>) <hi>Wee may gather that that ſtarre was hid from them for a time, which ſeemeth to haue begunne, when they came into Iudea. Ex hoc &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Chryſ in opere imperfect in Matt. homilia. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>out of this place it appeareth, that when the ſtarre had brought the wiſe men ſomewhat neere to Ieruſalem it was hidden from them, that being forſaken of the ſtarre, they might be compelled to aske for Chriſt, and to manifeſt him alſo in Ieruſalem.</hi> Their light fayling them then, they ſoone went out of the right way, if a man walke in the night, he wil both ſtumble<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 10.11.</note>, and turne out of his way. And as theſe hauing loſt the ſtarre their guide, ſoone looſe their way, like the ſhip that without the <hi>Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus index,</hi> the ſea compaſſe or needle, would quickly run aſide vpon rocks and ſhelfes: ſo the ſhip of Chriſt the Arke of his Church, if hee the ſtarre of <hi>Iacob,</hi> the day ſpring from an high<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 1.78.</note>, ſhould not viſit it to giue light vnto it, if the day ſtarre of his Goſpell<note n="h" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19.</note>, ſhould not ſhine vnto it, to ſhew it the way, would neuer come into the hauen, where it would be, but either fall vpon the rocks of hereſie, or runne aground into the ſands of Impiety, where it would ſtick faſt, till it were broken in pieces with the violence of the waues of wickednes, like that ſhip that <hi>Pauls</hi> ſailed to Rome in<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 27.41.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14448:22"/>Now in that, when they know not whither to goe, they come to Ieruſalem to ſeeke for Chriſt, they haue both motiues and inducements in themſelues to doe ſo, and alſo God (who ſitteth at the ſterne, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruleth not only the falls &amp; infirmities, of his ſeruants, but alſo the impieties of the Prince of darkneſſe, and the children of diſobedience, for the fulfilling of his will, the ſhewing of his power, and declaring of his name &amp; glory<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 9.17.</note>) hath his hand, his worke and purpoſe herein. In themſelues they haue a double motiue. Firſt from naturall reaſon, euen the wiſdome of the fleſh, for where ſhould they ſeeke the King of the Iewes, but in the mother City of the Iewes, <hi>Which aboue the other Cities of Iudea, excelled amongſt all the inhabitants, as the head in the body</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ioſeph: de bell Iudaico. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>Hieruſalem ciuitas regia eſt &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Remigius</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Remig: in catena aurea.</note>) <hi>Ieruſalem is the Kingly City, and they beleeued that ſuch a child ought not bee borne, but in the Kingly City. Humano ſenſu &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Leo ſerm. in Epiphan.</note>.) <hi>By humane reaſon they imagined, that the birth of the King which was ſhewed vnto them, was to bee ſought in the Kingly City.</hi> Here then by the way (for I meane not to inſiſt vpon the point) we may obſerue, that if the wiſdome of the fleſh be our leader in the things of God, it will ſoone miſlead vs. For the world with all her wiſdome, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know, finde out the things of God<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> the naturall man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>doth not receiue, apprehend the things of the Spirit of God</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note>. If fleſh and bloud be our Counſellor, it will ſoone miſtake with <hi>Nicodemus</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh 3.9.</note>, in the great Miſteries of godlineſſe. For as the bands of men, which <hi>Benhadad</hi> King of Syria ſent to lay hands on the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> being ſmitten with blindeneſſe, in ſtead of comming to Dothan, went into the midſt of Samaria<note n="h" place="margin">2. King. 6.19.</note>, ſo there hangeth ſuch a miſt of naturall blindneſſe ouer all the eyes of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> that in ſtead of ſeeking a Chriſt made of no reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are ready to dreame of, and ſeeke a Chriſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14448:23"/>all glorious without, rejoycing in the fleſh, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>With great pompe and Solemnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond motiue that they had to ſeeke <hi>Chriſt</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> is from that dimme light, that had ſhined vnto them in religion, from that little taſte that they had of the word of God, concerning him that was to come into the World.</p>
            <p>They had heard of that Prophecy of <hi>Balaam</hi> a <hi>Gentile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpread abroad amongſt the Gentiles, that a Starre ſhould come out of Iacob, and a Scepter riſe out of Iſraell.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 24.17.</note> No wonder therefore, that ſeeing his <hi>Starre,</hi> they ſhould acknowledge his byrth, <hi>quam vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Maximus</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Maxim <hi>9.</hi> homil. <hi>3.</hi> in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</note>) <hi>which if through Gods reuealing of it, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile could foretell, in like manner alſo a Gentile might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge.</hi> Now <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> being the Citty of God, of the great King,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal 48.12.</note> the perfection of beautie: the Ioy of the whole Earth,<note n="d" place="margin">Lam. 2.15.</note> of which glorious things were ſpoken<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 87.3.</note> euen amongſt the Heathen, wherein God had ſet his Temple, and put his name, and wherein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout men, of euery nation vnder Heauen, that came from farre for Gods great and glorious name, vſed to dwell<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 2.3.</note> and whither the Eunuch, and other deuout men came to worſhip:<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 8.27.</note> where ſhould they (iudging according to the appearance, of that ſlender light that had ſhined vnto them) ſeeke for this Starre of <hi>Iacob,</hi> (whoſe byrth they acknowledged, by this new Starre concurring with the prophecie) but in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> where God would be worſhipped? <hi>Quare veneru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolymam? &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Haymo</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Haymo in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit. huius Euan</note>) <hi>Why came they to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem? They were Aſtrologers, when they ſaw a Starre which they had not ſeene before, they beganne to thinke what manner of Starre it might bee! when they thought this, they remembred the Prophecy of Balaam! when they reade this; and ſaw that the Starre was riſen, they preſently knew that the Lord was borne in Iudea: therefore they come to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14448:23"/>And indeede it was the cuſtome of Forraigne Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that when they ſaw any wonder in the Heauens: they would goe, or ſend to Hieruſalem, where the knowledge of God was, as they did in the time of Hezekiah, when the Sunne went back tenne degrees.</hi> For <hi>Merodach Baladan,</hi> King of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſent Ambaſſadors to him, to enquire of the wonder that was done in the Land<note n="a" place="margin">2 Chro. 32.31.</note> 
               <hi>Ad inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum prodigium prout obſeruatum fuerat a Chaldeis,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iunius in <hi>2.</hi> reg. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to inquire of the wonder, as it had beene obſerued by the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans.</hi> Now in that they had ſome ſhew, ſome colour in Religion, for this miſtaking of the place of <hi>Chriſts</hi> byrth: wee may heere bee inſtructed, how eaſie it is to erre in the beſt matters, for as the blinde man but halfe enlightened, tooke men to bee trees,<note n="c" place="margin">Marke 8.24.</note> ſo men newly conuerted, being but Babes: in whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> is but begunne to be formed, and not able to diſcerne the things that differ, may eaſily take ſhaddows, for ſubſtances, likely hoods and outward appearances, for truth it ſelfe, wilde grapes for good fruite, a ſhew of godlineſſe: for the power of godlineſſe it ſelfe. For thus in matters of our holy faith, and ſaluation, many that are vnlearned: children in vnderſtanding, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, to take that filthy harlot of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the true ſpouſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that denne of theeues, cage of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane Birds for the Temple of God, Antichriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Temple of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for his Vicar, his Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard ſet ouer his houſe, Satans meſſenger: for Angells of light, Wolues in Sheepes cloathing: for faithfull Paſtors, the Idoll of the <hi>Maſſe:</hi> for the true propicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> baſtard Sacraments of mans inuention: for legitimate Sacraments of <hi>Chriſts</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, lip-labour in an vnknowne tongue: for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout praying; will-worſhip, which God hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: for a reaſonable ſeruing of him; diſtruſt, and doubtfullneſſe of Saluation: for a ſauing faith; calling vpon the Saints and Angells, falling downe before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14448:24"/>Stocks, and Stones, for the way by which in humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde they muſt goe vnto God, and in a word their whole heape of Gibeonitiſh traſh,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioſ. 9.4.</note> and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for auncient vnwritten verities comming from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Againe in matters of chriſtian conuerſation, men are eaſily beguiled to take worldly ſorrow for God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow, <hi>Eſaus</hi> Teares, for <hi>Peters</hi> Teares, <hi>Ahabs</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, for <hi>Manaſſehs</hi> Repentance, Phariſaicall gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, for good Almes-dooing, Lip-labour for Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Spirit, Phariſaicall boaſting before God and the World, for ſound and heartie Thanksgiuing; drawing neere vnto God with the Lippes, for draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere vnto God with the Heart, Yea, and euery Vice: for ſome ſeeming Vertue. <hi>Superbia celſitudinem imitatur, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>Pride imitateth mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie, Curioſitie ſeemeth to affect a deſire of knowledge, Ignorance alſo is couered with the name of Innocency, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality carrieth a ſhew of Liberality. Vitia nobis ſub Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum nomine obrepunt,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Seneca Epiſt. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>Vices creepe on vs vnder the name of Virtues, Raſhneſſe lurketh vnder the title of Fortitude, and the Coward is taken for a Warie man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then wee may bee ſo quickly deceiued with the hurtfull weedes of the Field beeing like to the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Hearbs of the Garden, it ſhall bee good for vs not to iudge according to the outward appearance: but to weigh and trie euery thing in the Balance of the Sanctuary, and to hold faſt only: that which is truely and certainly good.<note n="d" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid to his Brethren, about their ſelling of him into <hi>Egypt, It was not you that ſent mee hither: but God</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 45 8.</note> not they alone, but God had his finger, his worke in it, and they did whatſoeuer his hand, and his Counſell determined before to bee done:<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 4.28.</note> ſo it was not of themſelues alone that they came to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14448:24"/>Ieruſalem to ſeeke Chriſt, but it was the Lords doing, who bringeth them hither that hee might prouoke Iſraell to iealouſie by them that were no people<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10 19.</note>, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feruntur Magi &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hierome</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> expoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>) <hi>the wiſe men are brought by the leading of a ſtarre into Iudea, that the Prieſts, being asked of the Wiſemen where Chriſt was borne, might become inexcuſable about his comming. Fides iſta Magorum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Epiphan.</note>) <hi>this faith of the Wiſemen, is the Iewes condemnation: they beleeued their owne Prophet</hi> (Balaam) <hi>theſe would not beleeue ſo many Prophets: they confeſſe him being an aliene, theſe doe not acknowledge him being their owne, hee was knowne of the Gentiles, he was not knowne of the Iewes; hee was acknowledged by the Church, hee was not acknowledged by the Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They come to Ieruſalem, <hi>ad confuſionem Iudaeorum</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author<note n="d" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in opere imperſ: hom <hi>2.</hi> in Epiph.</note>) <hi>for the confounding of the Iewes, becauſe the Gentiles being confirmed onely by the ſight of a ſtarre, did ſeeke Chriſt euen in forraigne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys; and the Iewes reading from their infancie the prophecies concerning Chriſt, did not receiue him being borne in their coaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe hath <hi>Maximus</hi> a pleaſant and paſſionate Apoſtrophe, a turning of his ſpeech vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iewes. <hi>Quouſque Iudaee duriſſirre</hi> (ſaith hee<note n="e" place="margin">Maximus hom. <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Epiphan.</note>.) <hi>How long, O thou obſtinate Iewe, wilt thou continue with thine eare ſtopped, thine eyes ſhut, and thine heart faithleſſe? Beholde now, after thoſe Sermons of the Patriarches, after the Prophecies of the Prophets, Chriſt is alſo preached by the Gentiles. If thou refuſeſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thy fathers, who from the beginning of the World, haue by infinite Holy Prophecies, ſpoken of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the euerlaſting King, beleeue theſe men now at length which teſtifie, not that hee ſhall bee borne here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but that hee is already borne with thee, and for thee. What great frowardneſſe, and deadly obſtinacy is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14448:25"/>there in thine heart, that thou onely heareſt not that which all men ſpeake, thou onely abhorreſt that which all men beleeue, thou onely makeſt none account to ſee that which ſhineth out of heauen? A Virgin hath conceiued with thee, and a ſtranger taketh notice of the birth of thy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, the Angels words cannot perſwade thee to thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet one ſtarre bringeth the wiſemen vnto thy Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, then thorough the hardneſſe of heart that was come vnto Iſraell<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 11.25.</note>, Chriſt reueiled vnto them by theſe wiſe men, was a ſauiour of death vnto death vnto them. Thus, hee could not haue done more to his Vineyard then hee did, but it would not bring foorth good but wilde grapes onely<note n="b" place="margin">Iſai. 5.4.</note>, thus, hee would haue gathered the children of Ieruſalem to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as an henne gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, and they would not<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 23.37.</note>. Beloued, let mee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the words of exhortation to our ſelues: let vs not make Iſraels ſinne ours, Iſraels puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ours. Let there not bee ſuch a ſpirit of ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vpon vs, that Chriſt ſhould bee preached vnto vnto vs, as the great booke of the creatures is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the world, to make vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note>, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apologie, without excuſe for our ſelues,</hi> that his peace ſhould be preached vnto vs, and wee not bee the ſonnes of Peace<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 10.5.6.</note> that his Kingdome ſhould come neere vnto vs, and wee be deeper in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of hell in the laſt day<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 10 11.12.</note> then Sodome it ſelfe, but let vs with <hi>Zacheus</hi> receiue him ioyfully<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 19.6.</note>, and when wee are poſſeſt of him, let vs, with the two Diſciples that went to <hi>Emaus,</hi> conſtraine him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with vs<note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 24.29.</note>, vſe a kinde of holy importunity and violence (ſuch a violence as the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuffereth<note n="i" place="margin">Matt. 11.12.</note>) to keepe him in our coaſts, that ſo he may giue vnto vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>right or prerogatiue,</hi> to bee the ſons of God<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note>, euen to be heires of God and ioynt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14448:25"/>heires with him, of that inheritance incorruptible, vndefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerued in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for vs by him, to whom with the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons and one God bee a ſcirbed greatneſſe, and Power, and Glory, and Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Maieſty now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14448:26"/>
            <head>The third Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the earthly buildings, he that begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to build and finiſheth not, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe a mockingſtocke to the beholders<note n="a" place="margin">Luk 14.29.30.</note>. Let it not then be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous vnto any, that I (a poore builder in the houſe of God, according to the meaſure of the grace that is giuen to me<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10.</note>) ſhould finiſh the worke that I haue begunne, and adde the roofe to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation that I haue laide vpon this text already.</p>
            <p>Now in the bill (as it were) of the particulars of this text (the totall ſumme and ſubſtance whereof, is a narration, a deſcription of a ſolemne comming and enquiry for the new borne Meſſiah) there remaines vpon mine account that I made of them, the three laſt to be ſcanned, and examined, namely the forme of the enquiry. <hi>Where is hee that is borne. King of the Iewes?]</hi> The moouing cauſe that brought them to come and enquire, <hi>for wee haue ſeene his ſtarre in the Eaſt]</hi> and laſtly the finall cauſe and end of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>and are come to worſhip him.]</hi> Of theſe three, if I render an account at this time, the whole bill will be perfectly diſcuſſed, and cleared in euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. To peruſe and ſcanne them in their order, I muſt firſt beginne with the forme of enquiry that they make here ſaying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where is he that is borne King of the Iewes?]</hi> There is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14448:26"/>a little diuerſity about the reading and meaning of theſe words, ſome reading them according to the courſe of the words in the originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Where is he that is borne King of the Iewes,</hi> and interpreting them, that the Wiſe-men ſhould aske, for him, <hi>qui minimè natus eſt &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Beza in locum.</note>. <hi>Who was not borne a priuate man, but the King of the Iewes, from his very cradle, and factitio regi naturalem opponere</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Maldonat. in locum.</note>, <hi>and oppoſe the naturall King againſt the made King:</hi> others, <hi>where is the King of the Iewes that is borne</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Beza, Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Geneua tranſlat.</note>, and maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that there is a traiection or tranſpoſing of the words from their Grammaticall order in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, according to that manner of ſpeaking <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 19.38.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed bee hee that commeth a King in the name of the Lord</hi> (for ſo wee muſt turne the words, if we follow the literall order) for, <hi>bleſſed hee the King that commeth in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in that they ſtile this <hi>new borne Babe King of the Iewes,</hi> It may ſay with <hi>Auſtin, multa conſideranda ſunt hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>66.</hi> do diuerſis.</note>. I is worthy our conſideration to examine, Firſt why they call him the <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> not by any other name. Secondly what King they meane him to be? For theſe are good and profitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, and none of thoſe vaine and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble queſtions, which in theſe Lectures I haue profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhunne. For the firſt, if the prophecy of <hi>Balaam</hi> a Gentile, diſperſed amongſt the Gentiles, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the ſtarre to giue them the knowledge of this hidden myſtery (which is the iudgement of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity) then without controuerſie this title was built vpon the foundation thereof, for it giueth vnto him Kingly power and preheminence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There ſhall come a Starre out of Iacob, and a Scepter ſhall ariſe out of Iſraell, and ſhall ſmite the corners of Moab, and deſtroy all the children of Sheth! out of Iacob ſhall hee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14448:27"/>come, that ſhall haue dominion, and ſhall deſtroy him that remayneth of the Citty,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 24.27.19.</note> 
               <hi>Scepter, hauing Dominion, Smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Deſtroying,</hi> giue vnto him the markes, Name, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a King.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Starre that appeared vnto them, did portend, that hee that was borne was a King. At the byrth and death of great Princes, there haue beene oftentimes. <hi>Oſtenta a ſole, Lunâ &amp; Stellis: Signes and wonders from the Sunne, Moone, and Starres.</hi> To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in one or two amongſt many, <hi>Mithridates Rex</hi> (ſaith <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtine</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtin lib. <hi>37.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. or. in mit.</note>) <hi>In the yeare that King Mithridates was borne in, and in that that he beganne to raigne in, a blazing Starre at both times ſo ſhined, for ſeauentie dayes, that all the Heauens ſeemed to bee on fire.</hi> And becauſe happilie wee will bee moſt delighted with our owne Hiſtories herein. <hi>Sub Henerico tertio, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Polid. virg. lib. <hi>16.</hi> Hiſtor. Anglic.</note> 
               <hi>In the Raigne of Henry the third, King of England, Otho the Popes Legate, Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Henrys ſonne, Edward, about whoſe birth there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Starre of great bigneſſe, certaine dayes before the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Sunne, which was carried alongst the Heauens with a ſwift and ſpeedy courſe, ſometimes ſhewing fire before it, ſometimes leauing ſmoake behinde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this, as the finger of God (as I formerly ſhewed) brought them to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to take away all excuſes from the Iewes, ſo it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>without Gods doing:</hi> that they heere enquire for the new borne <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> vnder the name of the King of the Iewes. God would hereby let the Iewes ſee (though ſeeing they would not ſee) that hee whome they looked for was come into the World. For both in the prophecies that went before of him, hee is ſtiled and called a <hi>Ruler,</hi> out of <hi>Bethlehem Ephrata</hi> ſhall hee come forth to mee, that is to bee a <hi>Ruler</hi> in <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Micah. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>A King, reioyce O Daughter of Zion, Shout O Daughter of Hieruſalem, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy King commeth vnto thee,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Zach. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>and inneſted with all princely power for al eternitie: Vnto vs a Childe is borne, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14448:27"/>vs a Sonne is giuen, and the gouernment ſhall bee vpon his ſhoulders-of the increaſe of his gouernment and peace there ſhall be none end,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa 9.6.7.</note> and alſo the Iewes themſelues, were fully perſwaded, that the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> when he came would deliuer <hi>Iſraell</hi> out of their Temporall ſeruitude,<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 24.21.</note> and reſtore againe the kingdome to <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 1.6.</note> out of which perſwaſion, at one time they would haue made him a King<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 6.15.</note> by force, at another time they cryed out in their ſolemne acclamations to him: <hi>Bleſſed is the King that commeth in the name of the Lord.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 19.31.</note> Therefore God would haue <hi>Chriſt</hi> publiſhed vnto them by the name of the King of the Iewes, <hi>vt ad ſuſcipiendum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem beneficio ſibi blandiente concurrant:</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Chriſoſt. homil. <hi>7.</hi> in Matt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they runne to receiue this King, through the alurement of the benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is to be conſidered, what manner of King they meane him to bee, whither a King of this World: which hee himſelfe denieth,<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 18.36.</note> or elſe the King eternall<note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>the onely Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>Quid Magi venientes dixerunt, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>31.</hi> de tempore.</note>) <hi>Why doe theſe wiſe-men that come ſay: where is he that is borne King of the Iewes? What meaneth this? Were there not ſo many Kings of the Iewes heretofore? Why doe they ſo greatly deſire to know, and adore the King of another Nation? They would neuer ſeeke after this with ſo great deuotion, deſire it with ſo zealoas affection, if they did not acknowledge him King of the Iewes, who is alſo the eternall King.</hi> And to the ſame effect hee ſpeaketh,<note n="l" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>35.</hi> de tempore.</note> 
               <hi>Non vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp;c. Theſe farre ſtrangers, and aliens altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from that Kingdome, could neuer thinke that they did owe ſo great honour to ſuch a King of the Iewes, as was wont to bee there: but they had learned that ſuch an one was now borne; by the worſhipping of whome they doubted not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine theire ſaluation before God: for he was not of age to be flattered by man, he ſate vpon no royall Seate, hee wore no purple, no Crowne glittered upon his Head, no pompous Trayne of his, nor terrible Army, no fame of his glorious
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14448:28"/>Battells drew theſe men from farre Countries vnto him, with ſo earneſt deſire to worſhip him. Hee lay in a Manger, a Childe newly borne, little in Body, contemptible for his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, but in that little one was hid ſome great things.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="a" place="margin">Cypr. ſerm. de Stella &amp; magis.</note> 
               <hi>profiteri regem &amp; Deum, profeſſe him to be both a King and God,</hi> and (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> alſo)<note n="b" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>1.</hi> ex variis in Mat</note> 
               <hi>aliud Oculis corporis, aliud viſu men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aſpiciunt, they behold one thing with the eyes of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, another thing with the eyes of their minde,</hi> Now when thus boldly, thus confidently, they propoſe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories in the Streetes of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and aske for the King of the Iewe; that was newly borne, euen in the hearing of <hi>Herod,</hi> (of whome I may ſpeake, as it was ſaid of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight) <hi>He entred like a Foxe and raigned like a Lyon,) iſtud nequaquam, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Chryſ. homil. <hi>6.</hi> in Mat.</note> 
               <hi>They could not be ignorant of this, that comming into a Citty wherein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother King raigned, by ſpeaking ſuch Words, and naming another King of that People, they would ſtirre vp a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Sword about their eares.</hi> Therefore the imperfect worke vpon <hi>Matthew</hi> that carrieth <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> name, queſtioneth and reſolueth this matter thus. <hi>Numquid neſciebant, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Chryſ. in opere imperf. hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Did they not know that Herod raigned in Hieruſalem? Vnderſtood they not the Iuſtice of the Law? that whoſoeuer, whileſt one King is aliue, pronunceth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee King, and adoreth him, looſeth his life as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of an Vſurper, but whilſt they thinke vpon the king to come, they feare not the King preſent. Had they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Eyes the danger of Death, when they went about ſuch an vnlawfull thing: But they cared not for Death, if they had, they would neuer haue beene ſo bold. All this while they had not ſeene Chriſt, and yet were they readie to die for him, Oh happy wiſe-men, whom the preſence of a moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell King, before euer they knew Chriſt, became his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare then theſe worthies of the Gentiles, through faith, out of weakeneſſe, became ſtrong, a beleeuing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14448:28"/>ſinceerely in their hearts, confeſſe boldly with their Mouthes,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 4 13.</note> and like to <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeeing him that is inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 11.17.</note> feare not the wrath of a mortall King, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils, and who though hee kill the Body, cannot touch the Soule. They are then (as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid of old <hi>Iſraell</hi> in another caſe) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cor. 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>Patterns Enſamples</hi> to vs, to profeſſe with <hi>Timothy,</hi> the good profeſſion of our Faith before many Witneſſes,<note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.12.</note> euen the Eyes and View of the preſent World: and with <hi>Dauid,</hi> not to be aſhamed to ſpeake of Gods Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies before Kings,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 119.46.</note> not to ſwarue from Gods Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: though our Perſecutors, and Oppreſſors were many.<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 119 157</note> Heerein wee muſt be followers of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the Author and finiſher of our Faith, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed a good confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> the Iudge that condemned him,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.23.</note> and of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Faithfull, who built Alters to the Lord, and called vpon the name of the Lord, when the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanite,</hi> an Idolatrous Nation, that ſerued other Gods, was in the Land.<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 12.6.7.</note> For then wee eſpecially ſhew that the loue of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in vs, when we abide with him in tribulation, that wee come to him ſinceerely, when wee take vp the Croſſe and follow him,<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 16.24.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſi tunc a Dei Teſtamonijs non declines, cum te nullus perſequitur. It is no great matter if then thou goeſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray from Gods Commandements, when no man perſecuteth thee.</hi> It is no great matter to bee as reſolute as <hi>Peter,</hi> when no daunger is at hand; to march vnder the banner of religion, when authority alloweth it, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and proſperity followeth it, but then to indure when the heate of the Day ariſeth, when the firie try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all commeth. is a proofe of our rooting and grounding in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The Deuill himſelfe knoweth that Trouble is the beſt Triall of Religion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thinking <hi>Iob</hi> to bee but a Temporizer, one that ſerued God for wordly neede, hee would haue him
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14448:29"/>tryed by aduerſity, <hi>Lay now thine hand vpon all that hee hath, and he will curſe thee to thy face</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 1.11.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Scilicet vt fulvum ſpectatur in ignibus aurum,</l>
               <l>Tempore ſic duro eſt, inſpicienda fides.</l>
               <l>Good gold from droſſe is in the ſornace tri'de,</l>
               <l>And faith from falſehood in trouble deſcri'de.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſouldiers courage is not ſo well ſeene in the campe, as in the battaile, when they cloaſe together, <hi>Pede pes denſuſque viruir, foote by foote, and man cloaſe with man.</hi> The marriners skill is not ſo well diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Cum placidum ventis ſtabit mare, When there is not a wagge of winde,</hi> as when <hi>vnâ Euruſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Notuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ruunt, creber<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> procellis Africus &amp;c. When all the windes hurry together.</hi> And the conſtancy and courage of the ſouldier of Ieſus Chriſt, is beſt ſeene and ſhowne, when tribulation ariſeth, when he can indure to the end, though he be hated of all men for Chriſts ſake<note n="b" place="margin">Matt. 10.22.</note>, It is the proteſtation of the Church of the Iewes, <hi>That their heart was not turned backe, nor their ſteps declined from Gods way, though God had ſore broken them in the place of Dragons, and couered them with the ſhadow of death, that they had not forgotten the name of their God, nor holden vp their hands to any ſtrange God, though for his ſake they were killed all the day long, and counted as ſheepe for the ſlaughter</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal 44.18.19.20.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>Shidrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bednego,</hi> would not forſake the Lord their God whom they ſerued, to fall downe before the idole that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had ſet vp, though the Kings anger were the meſſenger of death vnto them, but were euen <hi>fortiores ignibus, ſtronger then the fire it ſelfe</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note>, <hi>Daniell</hi> would not intermit his ordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions, which he had formerly vſed, no not for a little time, though the decree of his caſting into the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Denne were ſigned, and vnalterable, according
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14448:29"/>to the Law of the Medes and Perſians<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 6.</note>. Let vs not then be aſhamed of Chriſt and his Goſpell, when for the ſame, we come before the <hi>Herodes,</hi> the Princes of this world, but let vs confeſſe him boldly before them, who when they haue killed this mortall body the baſer part cannot come neere our immortall ſoule the better part.</p>
            <p>And let vs not with <hi>Nichodemus</hi> be ſuch cowardly profeſſors, that wee ſhould come to h m by night<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note>, doing the workes of light in the darkeneſſe, nor with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> bee his Diſciples in hidde-locke for feare of trouble<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh 19 38.</note>, nor with the Parents of the blinde man<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 9.22.</note>, and many of the Iewes beleeue in him, but not dare to confeſſe him, for feare of being put out of the Synagogue<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 12.42.</note>: but let vs be ſtronge in the Lord, and in the power of his might, that we may be able to ſtand and withſtand in the euill day<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 6.10.13.</note>: let vs with <hi>Paul</hi> be ready not be bound onely, but alſo to die at Ieruſalem for the name of the Lord<note n="g" place="margin">Act 21.11.12.13.</note>: not paſſe for all that may happen, nor reckon our life deare, ſo that we may fight the good fight of Faith and a good Conſcience, and let vs caſt our expences, count what it will coſt vs, and reſolue to indure the heate of the day, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> did to beare whatſoeuer the Empreſſe <hi>Eudoxia</hi> would inflict vpon<note n="h" place="margin">Hiſtor. tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith he<note n="i" place="margin">Chryſ. in Epiſt. ad Cyriaeum Epiſcopum.</note>,) <hi>If the Empreſſe will baniſh mee, let her baniſh me, the earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe thereof. If ſhee will ſaw me aſunder, let her, I haue</hi> Eſay <hi>for an example. If ſhe will throw mee into the Sea, I remember</hi> Ionas. <hi>If ſhe will caſt me into the Fornace, I haue the three Chrildren that counſell me this. If ſhe will caſt me to wilde beaſts, I remember</hi> Daniell <hi>caſt to the Lions in the Denne. If ſhee will ſtone mee, let her, I haue</hi> Stephen <hi>the firſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre. If ſhe will take mine head, let her take it, I haue</hi> Iohn <hi>the Baptiſt. If ſhee will take my goods, let her take them, naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14448:30"/>return. The Apoſtle telleth me, that God accepteth not the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man, and, if I ſhould yet pleaſe men, I were not the ſeruant of Chriſt, and</hi> Dauid <hi>armeth me ſaying, I ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Kings and was not aſhamed.</hi> I haue beene ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accountable for the firſt particular, I paſſe to the next: the moouing cauſe that bringeth them to come and enquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For we haue ſeene his ſtarre in the Eaſt.</hi>] Of all the ſenſes, wherewith God hath indued man for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of nature, there are two, the hearing and the ſeeing, that are as windowes, wherby he reueileth Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine miſteries, and conueieth ſupernaturall truthes vnto the minde. For by hearing he acquainteth vs with his will and word, <hi>faith commeth by hearing</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note>, and <hi>let h m that hath an eare, heare what the ſpirit ſaith to the Churches</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Reu. 2.7.</note>. And by ſeeing his workes, either of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the creation and preſeruation of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, or beyond nature, in the wonders that he doth: we learne that the workeman is God alone, that none is like him<note n="c" place="margin">Iſai. 46.9.</note>, and that he is to be praiſed for his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes to the ſonnes of men<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 107 8.</note>. <hi>The inuiſible things of God, euen his eternal power &amp; God-head, are cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeene, being vnderſtood by the things that are made</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note>. <hi>The heauens doelare the glory of God, and the firmament ſheweth his handy worke</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 2.11. &amp; 6.14.</note>. And by miracles, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our manifeſted his glory, and wrought faith in the hearts of them that ſaw them, as here, <hi>Noua ſtella no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum adventaſſe hominem reuelabat</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Max. hom. <hi>2.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>. <hi>A new ſtarre ſhewed that a new man was come.</hi> And they call it heere <hi>his ſtarre, quia quamvis &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Idem. homil. <hi>4.</hi> in Epiph.</note>, <hi>becauſe although all the ſtarres being created by him are his, yet this was Chriſts more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly, becauſe it did ſpecially ſhew his comming. And the reſt of the ſtarres were made, that they might diſtinguiſh the times, and courſes of this world, but this was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to appeare, that the Lord of the world, and the time of heaxenly Kingdome was at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:14448:30"/>
Now, <hi>eo naſcente &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>34.</hi> de temp.</note>, <hi>at his birth, a new light was reueiled in a ſtarre, at whoſe death the olde light was vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Sunne. At his birth, the heauens ſhined with a new honor, at whoſe death hell trembled with a new feare, at whoſe reſurrection his Diſciples were inflamed with a new loue, at whoſe aſcenſion the Heauens obeyed with a new ſeruice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our Sauiours birth was not onely honoured with this new ſigne from heauen (a thing which at another time the Phariſes deſired<note n="b" place="margin">Matt 16.1.</note>, though now it would not worke vpon them) but alſo, <hi>omnia noua</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>1.</hi> ex varijs in Matt.</note>) <hi>All things both new and going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond humane admiration, doe meete in the Lords byrth. An Angell ſpeaketh in the Temple to</hi> Zachary, <hi>and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth that</hi> Elizabeth <hi>ſhall haue a ſonne. The Prieſt not beleeuing the Angell, is dumbe, the barren conceiueth, a Virgin bringeth a childe.</hi> Iohn <hi>being inſpired leapeth in his mothers wombe. Chriſt our Lord being borne, is told of by an Angel — the Angels were glad, and the ſheepe-heards reioyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were <hi>multa documenta</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Leo ſerm. <hi>5.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>) <hi>Many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which by manifeſt tokens declared that the Lord was borne, either when the Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>heard and beleeued, that ſhee ſhould conceiue by the Holy Ghoſt, and bring forth the Sonne of GOD, or when at her ſaluation</hi> Iohn <hi>Baptiſt being in his mothers wombe and not yet borne, leaped with a propheticall exultation, and did (as it were) crie in the wombe of his mother. Behold the Lambe of God which taketh away the ſinnes of the World, or when at ſuch time as the Angell told of the birth of the Lord, the ſheepe-heards were compaſſed about with the glory of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly army.</hi> Now for the queſtions wherewith the curioſity of man hath loaded this particular, what this ſtarre was, whether one or many, whether newly created, or one of the old ſtarres created from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, whether a reall ſtarre, or a Comet, or an
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14448:31"/>Angell in figure of a ſtarre, whether it was ſeated in the firmament or in the ayre, whether it roſe in the Eaſt, or they being in the Eaſt ſaw it in Iudea, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſaw it and none others, how it mooued, whether circularly or right forward, when it firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to appeare, and when it ceaſed, they are but <hi>aranearum telae, in quibus retexendis tempus non collocabo, Spider webbes, which I will not ſpend time to vnweaue;</hi> the knowledge of them will make vs neuer a whit neerer to heauen, and the ignorance of them will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hinder vs from comming there. Onely <hi>illud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitione dignum puto, vnde ad hunc illi potuerunt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum venire</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Chryſ. homil. <hi>6.</hi> in Matt.</note>) <hi>I thinke this point worth the asking how they could come to the vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that this ſtarre did portend the birth of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, <hi>&amp; quis eos in hoc ſuſcitaſſe credatur,</hi> and <hi>who may bee thought to haue ſtirred them vp hereunto.</hi> For ſolution whereof I may ſay, that beſides the prophecies, of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> (whereof I haue already ſpoken) of <hi>Daniell</hi> about the ſeuenty weekes &amp; the comming of the Meſſias<note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 9.24.26.</note>, (which by reaſon of the captiuity of Babilon were ſpread abroad amongſt the Gentiles) of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billaes (which though ſome condemne for fained, becauſe they ſpeake ſome things of Chriſt more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then the holy Prophets) yet Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> thinketh that they prophecied by the ſame Spirit of God to the Gentiles, by which the Prophets propheci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the people of the Hebrewes<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>18.</hi> de ciuit dei cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note>, of whom one ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Samia Sybilla.</note>.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Huma no quem Virgo ſinu inuiolata fouebit,</l>
               <l>Annuit hoc caelum rutilantia ſydera monſtrant.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Whom in her armes a Virgin pure ſhall hold,</l>
               <l>The heauen ſhewed, the ſhinning ſtarres foretold.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14448:31"/>
Beſides theſe I ſay that God did <hi>ſingulariter exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare illos, ſtirre them vp particularly. Magnitudinem ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificationis intelligunt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Leo ſerm. <hi>3.</hi> in Epiphan.</note>) <hi>They vnderſtand the depth of the meaning by diuine inſpiration, which did ſo worke in their hearts, that they could not be ignorant of the myſtery of this great Viſion, and that that, which was vnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall to their eies, might not bee vnknowne to their mindes.</hi> And ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> anſwereth his owne queſtion<note n="b" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>6.</hi> in Matt.</note>, <hi>This ſeemeth to me not to bee the ſtarres worke alone, but Gods alſo, by whom their minde was ſtirred vp hereunto, whom wee may read to haue done ſuch a thing in</hi> Cyrus <hi>King of Perſia, preparing him, and ſtirring him vp to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the people of the Iewes from the yoake of captiuity</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro. 36.22. and Ezra. 1.1.</note>, And to the ſame effect he ſpeaketh alſo, <hi>forte miratur aliquis &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Chryſ. homil. <hi>1.</hi> ex varijs in Matt.</note>, <hi>Happily ſome man may wonder how the wiſemen could know the birth of our Sauiour by the ſigne of a ſtarre! Wee ſay that this was the gift of Gods grace.</hi> And <hi>Baronius</hi> a great Rabbi amongſt our aduerſaries maketh no bones to ſay, that all the fathers agree that theſe <hi>Magi,</hi> were brought to Chriſt, as well by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward light of the Spirit, as by the outward light of the ſtarre<note n="e" place="margin">Baron. tom. <hi>1.</hi> Annal. pag. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>But to come out of the Laborinth of theſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to that which may miniſter edifying to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, as <hi>Moſes</hi> vpon the Mount Nebo<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.1.2.</note>, ſaw the glory of the Land of Canaan, ſo wee in this bringing of the wiſe men to Chriſt by a ſtarre, may as in a mount of viſions, ſee a two-fold glory of the Lord. Firſt a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his goodneſſe, in that he calleth them by a new ſtarre, that had abuſed all the old ſtarres to impiety and ſuperſtition, making the ſtumbling blocke whereby they fell, to be the ſtarre whereby they ſhould riſe againe. <hi>Quare per ſtellam</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Petrus Chryſo. Log. ſerm. <hi>157.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>&amp;c. Why by a ſtarre? That through Chriſt, the matter of their errour might be an occaſion of their ſaluation.</hi> Of his goodneſſe, I ſay, in that he doth as it were, <hi>vti foro ſerue the time</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:14448:32"/>here, fitting himſelfe to their diſpoſition, and catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fiſh by the baite wherewith it would ſooneſt be taken. <hi>Inquis oportuit mitti Prophetas potius</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Chryſoſt. bomil. <hi>6.</hi> in Matth.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>Thou wilt ſay that Prophets ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue beene ſent, but the Wiſemen would neuer haue beleeued Prophets, or that hee ſhould haue ſpoken to them with ſome voice from heauen, neither would they haue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much for that. Or that hee ſhould haue ſent an Angell, but happily they would haue ſlightly regarded him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God leauing all theſe, calleth them by thoſe things which cuſtome had made familiar vnto them, by his wonderfull gracious carriage of the matter, euen ſtooping to he ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men.</hi> And a little after, <hi>and ſo in imitation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> Paul <hi>taking occaſion from the Altar, diſputeth with the Gentiles, and bringeth forth teſtimonies out of their owne Poets; and for a while preacheth Chriſt to the Iewes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forbidding of circumciſion, and from the ſacrifices tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the beginning of his doctrine for them that yet liued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law. For becauſe euery one is greatly in loue with his owne cuſtome, both God, and the teachers that hee ſent for the ſaluation of the world, take to themſelues matter to ſpeake of from the cuſtome of euery nation. Thinke it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ſtrange matter, that the Wiſemen are called by a ſtarre. Quoniam Aſtrologierant &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theophylact</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Theophyl. in hoe Euangel.</note>.) <hi>Becauſe the Wiſe men were Aſtrologers, therefore God bringeth them by a familiar ſigne, as hee brought</hi> Peter <hi>a Fiſher man by a multitude of fiſhes vnto the name of Chriſt, and cauſed him to wonder.</hi> And ſo <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt vſed Baptiſme<note n="c" place="margin">Muſcul. in locum.</note>, a matter familiar to the Iewes (for waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was much in requeſt with them<note n="d" place="margin">Mar. 7.1.6.</note>) that thereby he might prepare a people to the Lord. Thus doth God (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>ad ſe homines miris mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis adducere, bring men vnto him after wonderfull ſorts,</hi> and becommeth all things to all men, that by ſome meanes he might win ſome of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly we may ſee heere a glory of our Lord
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14448:32"/>and Sauiours greatneſſe, in that his baſeneſſe in the fleſh, his being in the forme of a ſeruant, is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied ſtill with ſome markes, of his Deity, of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the forme of God, that ſo where the one did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cauſe any occaſion of errour,</hi> the other might <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>take away the errour againe</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gregor. Nazianz. in oral. <hi>2.</hi> de filio.</note>. For thus <hi>in praeſepe iacebat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>30.</hi> de tempore.</note>) <hi>he lay in a Manger, and yet brought the wiſe men from the Eaſt, he was hidden in a Stable, and yet acknowledged in the heauens, that being acknowledged in heauen, he might bee manifeſted in the Stable. Cum ipſe dominus noſter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Maximus</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Maximus homil. <hi>3.</hi> in Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>When our Lord according to the Law of mans birth, being a little one and an infant, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his cradle, and was wrapped in ſwadling clouts, yet then a wonderfull ſtarre from an high ſhewed his greatneſſe to the whole world.</hi> And <hi>Quamuis</hi> (ſaith he<note n="d" place="margin">Maximus homil. <hi>4</hi> in Epiphan.</note>.) <hi>Although hee couered his God-head with the Mantle of our body, yet heauen ſhewed him, and the earth knew him to bee God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> hath an excellent paſſage to ſhew how the glory of his god-head, went as it were, hand in hand with the meaneſſe of his man-hood from his cradle to his croſſe<note n="e" place="margin">Greg. Naz. vbi ſupra.</note>, I will recite it, though it be ſomewhat long.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He was borne of a woman, but a Virgin, that as man, this as God; he was carried in the wombe, but he is knowne to the Prophet being alſo in the wombe, and leaping before the Word by whom hee was made: Hee was wrapped in ſwadling clouts, but when hee riſeth hee pulleth off the cloathes, that he was buried in: Hee is laide in a Manger, but hee is glorified by the Angells, ſignified by the ſtarre, adored by the Wiſe men: Hee was made flie into Egypt, but hee maketh the idoles of Egypt flie: Hee had neither forme nor beauty to the Iewes, but to</hi> Dauid <hi>hee was more beautifull then the ſonnes of men, but vpon the Mountaine he ſhineth, and is brighter then the ſunne: Hee was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14448:33"/>as man, but he waſheth away ſinnes as God, but it was to Sanctifie the waters</hi> (and the Holy Ghoſt deſcendeth vpon him, and the Father giueth him a teſtimony as being God) <hi>he was tempted as man, but hee ouercommeth as God, but he biddeth vs bee of good comfort, becauſe hee hath ouercome the world: Hee was hungry, but hee fedde thouſands, but hee is the Bread of Life that came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: He was thirſty, but he cryed, if any man thirſt, let him come to mee — he was weary, but hee is the reſt of all them that are weary, and heauy laden. Hee is heauy with ſleepe, but vpon the Sea, he is light, but hee rebuketh the windes but hee lifteth vp</hi> Peter <hi>ready to bee drowned: Hee payeth tribute, but out of a fiſh, but he is King of them that require it. He is called a Samaritane, and one that is poſſeſſed with a Deuill — but he is acknowledged of the Deuils, he driu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out the Deuils, and ſendeth legions of Friends into the Deepe, and ſeeth the Prince of the Deuils falling as lightning. He is ſtoned, but not vanquiſhed. Hee asketh where</hi> Lazarus <hi>was laide, for he is a man, but hee raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> Lazarus, <hi>for he was God. Hee is ſold, and that very cheape, for thirty pieces of ſiluer, but hee redeemeth the World, and that with a great price, euen his owne bloud. Hee is weake and wounded, but he healeth euery diſeaſe &amp; euery ſickneſſe. Hee is brought to the Croſſe, and faſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to it, but by the Croſſe he reſtoreth life, but he ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Theefe that was crucified with him, and cauſeth darkneſſe, but the Veile of the Temple renteth, but the ſtones cleaue a ſunder, and the dead are raiſed: Hee dieth, but hee maketh aliue, and by death deſtroyeth death: He is buried, but he riſeth againe;</hi> Thus that no man might ſtumble at his humiliation in the fleſh, the glory of the God-head manifeſted it ſelfe ſtill therein.</p>
            <p>But that I may draw towards an end of mine account for the whole bill heere, I come to the laſt particular, which is the finall cauſe and end of their comming.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14448:33"/>
               <hi>We are come to worſhip him.]</hi> And this though the laſt in order, is the weightieſt of all the particulars heere in nature. For vpon it hangeth not onely the grace, but euen the goodneſſe and vertue of all that formerly here they doe, and of all the circumſtances, that make this worke of theirs ſo commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yea ſo admirable vnto vs. For it is a ruled caſe of the Logitians, that <hi>Vltimus finis ſolus perfecit tam agentem quam actionem: The chiefe end alone doth make perfect as well the doer, as the action,</hi> &amp; againe, <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis finis talis actio, ſuch as the end is, ſuch is the action;</hi> ſo that to haue come preſently vpon Chriſts birth, and that when bloody <hi>Herode</hi> raigned, to haue come ſo far a iourney, euen out of the Eaſt to Hieruſalem, the place that God had choſen to put his name in, to haue enquired ſo ſolemnely for the new borne King of the Iewes, and to haue beene ledde thither by the guiding of a ſtarre, had beene nothing if the end had not commended the action: yea had beene abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable rather then admirable, if they had come, not to worſhip him (as they both profeſſe and purpoſe) but to worry him, as <hi>Herode</hi> intended when hee would haue gone vnto him, howſoeuer hee pretended to adore him. Wee may heere then as in a glaſſe, ſee what ſhould be the very finall cauſe and end of our comming vnto Chriſt (who though he be not bodily preſent with vs, yet <hi>ſecundum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeſentiam maieſtatis</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. tractat. <hi>50.</hi> in Ioh.</note>, is euer in the aſſembly of his Saints) which is, to yeeld him the homage that we owe vnto him, the honour that is due vnto him, either in bringing our oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſacrifices vnto him, or in receiuing from him, the treaſures that hee doth impart vnto vs by his Word and Sacraments. All other ends that men propoſe to themſelues in comming vnto him, are not ends, but rather aberrations from the true end. And as it were better neuer to know the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14448:34"/>then after knowledge of it to turne from it<note n="a" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.21.</note>, ſo better it were, neuer to come to Chriſt at all, then to marre our comming in the end thereof, to cauſe that <hi>quod officio videtur bonum, in the worke ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be good,</hi> to be <hi>ipſo non recto fine peccatum, a ſinne for want of a right end</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iulianum pelagian. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>. For thus men doe, when ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their they come vnto him for the belly and for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as the people followed him for Loaues, and as <hi>Bernard</hi> complayning of pompe and luxury of the Clergy of Popery in his time ſaid <hi>pro huiuſmodi volunt &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Bernard ſermon <hi>37.</hi> ſuper Cantica.</note>.<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.26.</note> 
               <hi>For theſe matters they wilbe, and become rulers of Churches, Deanes, Archdeacons, Biſhops, Archbiſhops,</hi> or for honour and preferment like to <hi>Zebedeus</hi> ſonnes, who deſired to ſit one on his right hand, the other on his left hand in his glory<note n="e" place="margin">Mar. 10.37.</note>, or like to <hi>Diotrephes</hi> for loue of preferment<note n="f" place="margin">3. Epiſt. Ioh. 9.</note>, or of curioſity becauſe they would ſee ſome great workes wrought by him, as the Phariſees and Sadduces come to him, deſiring him that he would ſhew a ſigne from heauen<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 16.1.</note>, and as <hi>Herode,</hi> who deſired to ſee Chriſt, becauſe he hoped to haue ſeene ſome miracle done by him<note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 23.8.</note>, or of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, becauſe they would put a faire Vizard vpon a foule face, and couer their euill deeds with a good profeſſion, being (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>in ſuperficie boni, in alto mali, good in the out ſide, bad in the inſide,</hi> or of vaine glory, as our Sauiours brethren would haue had him gone vp to the feaſt of Tabernacles that he might be knowne openly<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 7.3.4.</note>, and that with the Phariſee they might ſeeme better and holier then other men<note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 18.11.</note>, that with <hi>Simon Magus</hi> they might ſeeme to be ſome great men<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 8.9.</note>, <hi>ſunt qui ſcire volunt, vt ſciantur</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Bernar ſerm. <hi>36.</hi> ſuper Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica.</note>) <hi>There are ſome that would haue knowledge that they might be knowne againe;</hi> or for their corporall neede onely, as the nine Lepers that roare out for mercy that they may be clenſed, but haue not a word of praiſe in their mouthes to glorifie
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14448:34"/>God with, when they are deliuered<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 17.17.</note>, or which is worſt of all, out of malice and miſchiefe, as the Phariſees Diſciples and the <hi>Herodians</hi> came vnto him to entangle him in his talke<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22.15.</note>, as the officers ſent by the High Prieſts, to take him<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 7.32.</note>, and as <hi>Iudas</hi> one of them that did eate bread with him to betray him<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 26.47.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſpeake ſomewhat of this honour that they giue here to Chriſt, it is the opinion of ſome<note n="e" place="margin">Caluin, Muſculus.</note>, that they giue vnto him ciuill adoration, as taking him to be a great Prince, not religious adoration, as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him to be God. But in mine vnderſtanding, both all Antiquity and the truth it ſelfe ſtand on the other ſide. <hi>Putas adoraſſent infantem &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Chryſ. in opere imperf. in Mat. homil. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>Thinkeſt thou that, they would haue adored an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant that did not vnderſtand the honour of adoration, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they had beleeued that there was ſome Diuine power in him. Therefore they gaue this honour, not to his Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that vnderſtood nothing, but to his God-head that knew all things. Nec apud ſenſus eorum</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>29.</hi> de tempore.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Neither in their vnderſtanding, doth the baſeneſſe of his birth diminiſh the glory of his God-head — with their eyes they ſee man, by their ſeruice they confeſſe him to be God — he was ſcene in the Manger, but hee did beare rule in Heauen. And therefore the Wiſemen humbled themſelues becauſe they ſaw the ſtarres doe him ſeruice. For they knew him to bee God, to whom the heauenly creatures yeelded their ſeruice.</hi> And <hi>Athanaſius</hi> reaſoneth well in this caſe <hi>Quomodo in ſtabulo &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Athanaſius lib. de incarnat.</note>. <hi>How doe they adore him that lay in a ſtable and a manger, if they imagine him to bee nothing but a man? How doth</hi> Herode <hi>ſay that he would adore him alſo? In vaine truely had God taught them by ſo vnuſuall a miracle, that they ſhould adore a man onely and not God alſo.</hi> It is then religious and diuine honour that they giue vnto him as God. Let me here then ſhew you a myſtery, which is how Chriſt being both
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14448:35"/>God and man is to bee adored. Although then the Godhead bee the propper obiect to which adoration is propperly directed, yet is not the Godhead adored without the manhood, but by reaſon of that ſtrict band of the perſonall vnion of the two natures Chriſt as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>God and man</hi> is to be adored with one only adoration, which adoration is giuen <hi>Obliquè,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt in Pſal. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct manner,</hi> to the manhood, in regard that it is the Manhood of the Word, and receiued into the vnitie of the ſecond Perſon, <hi>Dominum rerum creatarum</hi> (ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſus,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Athanaſ: contra Arrianos</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. We doe adore the Lord of all created things the Word being made fleſh: For although the fleſh of it ſelfe be a part of things created, yet it is become the body of God; neither therefore doe wee adore this Body a part, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Word, neyther when wee are about to adore the Word, doe wee ſeparate it farre from the fleſh, but becauſe wee know (as hath beene ſaide) that the Word was made Fleſh: Wee acknowledge it now manifeſted in the fleſh to bee God. Who then is ſo graceleſſe, as to ſpeake ſo to the Lord, ſtand aſide from the Body that I may adore thee? Or who is ſo wicked that with the Iewes becauſe of his Body hee will ſay vnto him, Why doeſt thou beeing a Man, make thy ſelfe God?</hi> And for this adoring of the Word being made fleſh with one only adoration, wee haue the Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſme of Cyrill in the Epheſine Councell, which is the Third Oecumenicall Councell<note n="c" place="margin">Tom <hi>1.</hi> Concil. in Concil. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si quis, &amp;c. If any one doth not adore Emanuell with one only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration, and giue him one only glory, according to that, the Word was made fleſh, let him bee accurſed.</hi> It is then but a prophane noueltie both of words and Doctrines not only in the Papiſts, to giue a ſeuerall kind of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe (which they call Hyperdulia, a Seruice a ſteppe higher, then that which they giue to Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells) <hi>Soli humanitati Chriſti</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Bellarm. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de beatit. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>To the Manhood of Chriſt alone,</hi> but alſo in the Vbiquitaries, who contend for the adoration of the humanity of Chriſt properly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14448:35"/>and ſeuerally by it ſelfe<note n="a" place="margin">Barbaróſsa in quinquageſsima</note>, <hi>Adoratio Latriae</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Thomas in <hi>3.2.</hi> queſt. <hi>25.25.</hi> arti. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>.) <hi>The adoration of Latria or Diuine Worſhip, is not giuen to the humanity in reſpect of it ſelfe, but in reſpect of the Diuinity to which it is vnited,</hi> and <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Cyri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l ad Theodoſ.</note>, <hi>that wee doe not adore</hi> Emanuell <hi>as a man, for that were dotage, deceit and errour, for in this wee ſhould nothing differ from them which worſhip the creature &amp;c.</hi> Let them that haue eares then heare theſe deepe myſteries of their faith, and the Lord giue them vnderſtanding in all things, that they may ſo adore and glorifie God manifeſted in the fleſh, ſo honour the Sonne, ſerue the Sonne, that the Father may honour them<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 12.26.</note>, and giue them Glory with him. To this Father and Sonne with the Holy Ghoſt a Trinity in vnity, and an vnity in Trinity, be Honour and Power euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the third Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
